<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Mike Rooney]]></title>
  <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-07T20:05:31-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://mrooney.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mike Rooney]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Freelancing: A 6-Month Retrospective]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2012/07/01/freelancing-a-6-month-retrospective/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-01T23:13:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2012/07/01/freelancing-a-6-month-retrospective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the end of 2011 I quit my full-time job to pursue part-time freelancing in order to have more time and flexibility. It has now been 6 full months, so I&#8217;m writing this retrospective post in order to evaluate my progress and make improvements. Hopefully it will be useful or interesting to others!</p>

<h1>Why?</h1>

<p>In short, I felt that given a finite lifespan, there were more
fulfilling and enjoyable ways to spend some of my healthiest years than 40+ hour weeks in an
office.</p>

<p>More specifically, there were a few activities I wanted to spend more time doing: cooking, climbing, yoga, and Zen practice.</p>

<p>In review, here are the numbers between then and now:</p>

<ul>
<li>hours worked/week: 40-50 => 16-20</li>
<li>estimated vacation per year: 4 weeks => 12 weeks</li>
<li>meals cooked/day: ~0.7 => 2+</li>
<li>daily Zen practice (zazen): 15 minutes => 70 minutes, plus ~1 day a
week at the Fire Lotus Temple</li>
<li>weekly climbing / yoga: 0 => 2</li>
<li>monthly income: unchanged!</li>
</ul>


<p>Overall I&#8217;m quite happy with the time I&#8217;ve been able to set aside
for my interests, and feel healthier in body and mind!</p>

<h1>How?</h1>

<p>The first step was quitting my job, of course. Luckily in my case,
issues with my job, combined with having a responsible savings and leads on freelance work made this decision pretty easy. Curiously enough, I&#8217;m pretty sure reading Fahrenheit 451 put the final nail in the coffin.</p>

<p>Once I was freelancing part-time, the two main challenges I faced were money and time:
that is, budgeting for inconsistent and unpredictable income, and not squandering your
free time or becoming bored and falling into unnecessary work. There was also the issue of finding
freelancing jobs and maintaining a pipeline, but since that&#8217;s more
specific to whatever your skill is, I won&#8217;t touch on that here.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ll tackle the money and time issues separately.</p>

<h2>Money</h2>

<p>My favorite freelance budgeting technique has been to treat my freelancing
as a business. Here&#8217;s how.</p>

<p>Deposit your checks into a separate account, set aside
taxes, and then pay yourself a fixed amount monthly from this account. This way, if you
don&#8217;t work for a period of time or want to take vacation, it is very
clear how much money is remaining in your freelancing account. For
example, if you have $9,000 in your freelance account, and are paying yourself
$3,000/month (taxes are already taken out), you can go 3 months without another job if
necessary or desired.</p>

<p>The first part of this is easy. Open a separate checking or savings
account (this took about 30 seconds as an ING customer), deposit your
freelance checks into this account, then transfer out your estimated tax
withholding. For example, if you receive a check for $5,000 and you pay a 30%
tax rate, deposit the check in your freelance account and transfer out
$1,500 elsewhere for later tax payment, or alternately deposit the whole
check wherever is easiest and transfer $3,500 to your freelance account.</p>

<p>Next, figure out your monthly budget. I&#8217;ll leave this to you, but
mine included rent, utilities, health insurance, Roth IRA contributions,
transportation, groceries, eating out, subscription services, and
memberships. You&#8217;ll likely want to
multiply this number by ~1.3 to get a padding for savings and unexpected costs.</p>

<p>Once you&#8217;ve done this for a few months and have a padding in your freelance account, you
can even set up a recurring transfer for this amount on the first of each month from your
freelance account to your personal checking.</p>

<h2>Time</h2>

<blockquote><p>Being busy is a form of laziness—lazy thinking and indiscriminate action.</p>

<p>&#8211; Timothy Ferriss</p></blockquote>

<p>Because our culture so heavily emphasizes work and particularly having a full-time job for most of your life, unless you consciously and constantly evaluate how <em>you</em> want to spend your time, you&#8217;ll likely find yourself working more hours, regardless of necessity. Ferriss calls this &#8220;work for work&#8217;s sake,&#8221; and I wanted to avoid falling into this trap, instead finding fulfilling activities done for their own sake.</p>

<p>First, I set a limit of 20 hours of work per week. I provided this as
my maximum availability to any particular client. Recognizing the need for flexibility (clients might overlap, or I might just enjoy working on a particular
project for longer hours), I felt it was important to count any extra
hours towards the future, and limit how many hours I could accumulate.</p>

<p>The balance of my freelance account allowed me to clearly see if I actually needed to be working. I decided that 3 months of padding is sufficient security, and I promised myself that once I complete any job that lands me at a balance over that amount, I&#8217;ll take off until I hit that threshold again. If I didn&#8217;t have an external savings account with plenty to live on for a bit, or was finding it hard to find new work, I might feel safer with a 6-12 month padding. However, either way, I can still schedule work in advance to start after my vacation, so that I can take off without much risk or worry.</p>

<p>Next, I had to use my free time wisely. And just as importantly, realize how not to use it. A couple years ago I started a permanent information diet; quitting Google Reader alone I gained hours every week,
plus <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Shallows-Internet-Doing-Brains/dp/0393072223">a noticeable ability to concentrate again</a>. At first going to Reader/Twitter/Facebook/Tumblr were such mindless distractions for me that I had to block my access to them or I&#8217;d end up on them without realizing it, but after a few months those habits faded. I also found the same thing with TV shows, and made sure to be conscious of when a show felt like a chore to catch up on and stop watching it. Similarly with video games, when a game felt grindy, I&#8217;d uninstall it. Now I just watch about 2 shows a week, and ended up completely uninstalling Steam and my Windows partition as I was never using them.</p>

<p>Additionally, I made a list of everything I wanted to accomplish, including recurring
and one-time events. For recurring events, a site like <a href="http://www.joesgoals.com">Joe&#8217;s Goals</a> is especially useful; I keep it as a permanent pinned tab in Chrome and it keeps me honest about how often I&#8217;m actually doing the activities I say I care about. The previously mentioned activities such as cooking,
climbing, yoga, reading, and Zen filled in most of the time nicely so
there was little opportunity for boredom, but
I also knocked out a few things
I&#8217;d long had on my to-do list including:</p>

<ul>
<li>taking an aerial acrobatics class</li>
<li>acquiring a proper chef&#8217;s knife and taking a knife skills class</li>
<li>learning how to raise hens for eggs and meat</li>
<li>beginning to learn Polish (I live in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greenpoint,_Brooklyn">Greenpoint, Brooklyn</a>)</li>
</ul>


<p>I also took the entire month of June off and spent it visiting friends
and family, some of whom I hadn&#8217;t seen in years. I ended up in York, Rochester, Austin, San Francisco, as well as upstate NYC for a
week of camping with my girlfriend and her parents. I stayed with
friends instead of in hotels, and used Amtrak instead of flying where
possible to keep costs low. I&#8217;ve also been
able to host family and friends visiting NYC on weekdays that I wouldn&#8217;t have
otherwise been able to spend time with.</p>

<h1>Downsides to Freelancing</h1>

<p>Okay, clearly I&#8217;m pretty happy freelancing, but like most systems that offer great flexibility, you have to do a little
more work yourself that salaried employment would otherwise handle for you:</p>

<ul>
<li>finding opportunities and turning them into contracts</li>
<li>tracking time, invoicing, and following up on checks

<ul>
<li><a href="http://stuntsoftware.com/onthejob/">On The Job</a> has been a wonderful tool for this, and has a free trial.</li>
<li>I&#8217;ve recently switched to <a href="https://mikerooney.freshbooks.com/refer/www">FreshBooks</a>, as it handles invoicing and payment tracking better including automatic recurring invoices and late fees, tracks expenses, has a great overview dashboard, and most importantly can generate a Profit &amp; Loss report which you&#8217;ll need each quarter for taxes. You can use it for free indefinitely for up to 3 active clients.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>paying for your own healthcare and vacation. These actually turned out
to be less expensive than I thought:

<ul>
<li>healthcare: at 40 hours per week * ~4.3 weeks per month, you can assume you are getting
a bonus of $1-$3 per hour for healthcare ($172-$516/month). So
working 20 hours a week, that&#8217;s $2-$6/hour you need to make up.</li>
<li>vacation: assuming 5 weeks of vacation/holiday/sick pay out of 52,
that&#8217;s about a 10% bonus.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>So as an example, a $100K salary, which corresponds to roughly $50 per
hour working 40 hours a week,
requires a freelancing rate of $56-58/hour to pay for healthcare and
time off. If I wanted to work
20 hours per week using this example, I&#8217;d double that to get a required
rate of $112-116/hour. I had no problem
doubling my previous rate as just a starting point, so these benefits were easily paid for and is what allowed me to dramatically cut hours without a
pay cut.</p>

<p>Healthcare is a big and challenging topic, so if you find this to be a
problematic point for you, there&#8217;s a whole chapter devoted to it in the
all-around very thorough book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1413313310/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=1413313310&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=metafood-20">Working for Yourself: Law &amp; Taxes for Independent Contractors, Freelancers &amp; Consultants</a>. The short version is that if you can get on your spouse&#8217;s plan, that&#8217;s a great option, and COBRA can also be used if affordable, and can be turned into a personal plan after 18 months. I decided to go with an individual plan, looking extensively at both freelancersunion.org and ehealthinsurance.com before choosing a plan from the latter.</p>

<h1>What&#8217;s next?</h1>

<p>Working part-time has been incredibly enjoyable, particularly having
entire days off to be out and about during the least crowded and least
expensive times (weekday afternoons)
instead of the busiest and most expensive (weekends). As long as I can
keep my pipeline full (and it looks like I&#8217;m set into 2013 at the
moment), I&#8217;d love to keep shooting for about 16 hours per week, taking a
month off after every three working.</p>

<p>I&#8217;d love to hear about your experiences in your work life, or any
questions or thoughts you want to share!</p>

<h1>Resources</h1>

<p>Based on the questions this post has generated, I&#8217;d suggest reading <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0307465357/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0307465357&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=metafood-20">The 4-Hour Workweek</a> if you are looking for motivation, inspiration, and practical tips for quitting your job, going remote, or finding other income streams. Once you are working for yourself, the aforementioned <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1413313310/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=1413313310&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=metafood-20">Working for Yourself</a> is great and covers laws, taxes, insurance, contracts, and everything else you&#8217;d need to know in very great detail!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dynamic URLs with Amazon S3's Static Website Hosting]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2012/06/23/dynamic-urls-with-amazon-s3s-static-website-hosting/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-23T21:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2012/06/23/dynamic-urls-with-amazon-s3s-static-website-hosting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you want to host a static website, Amazon S3&#8217;s <a href="http://docs.amazonwebservices.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/WebsiteHosting.html">Website Hosting</a> is a very cheap and affordable way. &#8220;Static&#8221; hosting may seem limited, but with Javascript and HTML5 capabilities, you can accomplish quite a bit without a traditional web server.</p>

<p>If you aren&#8217;t familiar with S3, the basic steps are:</p>

<ol>
<li>create a Bucket, which acts as a sort of directory of files,</li>
<li>upload files to your bucket, optionally making them public,</li>
<li>enable Website Hosting, providing an index and error page,</li>
<li>Amazon gives you a domain which serves your Bucket, which you can
then create a CNAME to from any of your domains.</li>
</ol>


<p>Now, for very literally pennies a month, you
have 99.99% uptime and 99.99999999% durability on your files, fast
bandwidth, all without a single server or process to worry about.</p>

<p>This can work well for a traditional static site, but what if you&#8217;d like
to have nice, dynamic URLs? Let&#8217;s create a simple example of
bgcolor.com. You want users to be able to specify the desired background
color via the URL. You could use query strings (bgcolor.com/?blue) or hashes (bgcolor.com/#blue) to
pass data to Javascript on your index page, but this isn&#8217;t likely to be
understandable or easy to memorize for the average non-technical person.</p>

<p>Enter S3&#8217;s &#8220;error&#8221; page. The page you specify as your error page will be
served on 404s, and importantly, served at the 404 URL itself. So we can
set both our index and error pages to the same page, and examine the URL
with Javascript to perform the correct routing, loading, or action. For
our bgcolor.com example, we can now allow users to type
bgcolor.com/blue. Let&#8217;s take a look:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">body</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">style</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">background</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nb">window</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">location</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">pathname</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">split</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And you&#8217;ve got it! Note that this technique doesn&#8217;t mean you lose the
ability to have an actual 404 page; you can have your URL logic be aware of an
invalid URL and update the page appropriately or redirect to a 404.html. Just Google &#8220;javascript url router&#8221; if you don&#8217;t want to write your own, as there are quite a few mature looking ones that already exist.</p>

<p>Enjoy! This is the technique I&#8217;m using to host <a href="http://zazen.rowk.com/">zazen.rowk.com</a>, and it
costs me $0.01/month (yes, one penny).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DNS: Root/Apex CNAMES in Practice]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2012/05/01/dns-root-slash-apex-cnames-in-practice/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-01T19:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2012/05/01/dns-root-slash-apex-cnames-in-practice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While there&#8217;s technically a limitation in the DNS specification that
says domain apexes need to be A records, it is often desirable to be
able to point it at another domain, and I wanted to break the common
misconception that this can&#8217;t be accomplished.</p>

<p>The simplest case is that you have a &#8220;naked&#8221; domain such as example.com
that you want to forward to www.example.com. While you can&#8217;t use a CNAME
for your apex, you can indeed accomplish this forward in practice. I
don&#8217;t mean to imply that there&#8217;s a magical way to have a CNAME for
an apex (though with the last AWS method, there kind of is), simply
that what you want to achieve is doable without pointing your apex
directly at application web servers.</p>

<h1>The Easy Way</h1>

<p>If all your want is to have example.com go to www.example.com, there&#8217;s
a free service called <a href="http://wwwizer.com/naked-domain-redirect">wwwizer</a> that does this for you. Simply set your
apex A record to 174.129.25.170. That&#8217;s it! It&#8217;s really that simple!</p>

<h1>The Slightly Harder Way</h1>

<p>You can do what wwwizer is doing yourself, and handle more cases than an
apex going to www, so let&#8217;s look at how that works. If you curl a domain
using <a href="http://wwwizer.com/naked-domain-redirect">wwwizer</a>, you&#8217;ll get an HTTP 301 to www.thatdomain.com. So all that
wwwizer is doing is using the host variable you send it when you request
thatdomain.com, and doing a 301 redirect to www.thatdomain.com.</p>

<p>Here&#8217;s an example nginx server directive that accomplishes this in a
generic fashion:</p>

<pre><code>server {
    listen 80;
    server_name _;
    return 301 http://www.$http_host$request_uri;
}
</code></pre>

<p>If you want more than a simple apex to www forward, you just need to
create a map of the domains to the desired CNAME, and you are good to
go. You can even still use DNS for this, so you have a single source of
truth, by using <a href="http://webpulp.tv/episodes/learn-how-tropo-built-a-huge-voice-cloud-while-using-dns-for-a-key-value-store">DNS as a key-value store</a>.</p>

<p>All you need to do is point your apex at an IP (or set of IPs) that have
a server configured to perform the appropriate 301s. At this point you
might be complaining that having to maintain a static IP is what you
were trying to avoid, and that&#8217;s fair. But it is important to note that
the A record(s) you use for your apex don&#8217;t have to run your
application, so you can simply throw nginx/apache on a service you
already keep highly available on a static IP (puppetmaster, internal DNS servers, et
cetera). This allows you to use a perhaps more stable and less ephemeral
set of IPs than web server IPs. Plus, multiple domains / applications
can share this server. And remember, if you just need naked ->
www redirection, just use wwwizer instead of worrying about this
yourself.</p>

<h1>The Amazon Way</h1>

<p>If you are using AWS, <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/route53/faqs/#Zone_apex">they support mapping a zone apex to an Elastic
Load Balancer</a> (ELB) via
their DNS provider Route 53. So this means even as your load balancer is
transparently replaced or scaled up and down, you don&#8217;t have to worry
about the IPs involved.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Diving into EC2 and Auto Scaling]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2010/12/21/diving-into-ec2-and-auto-scaling/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2010/12/21/diving-into-ec2-and-auto-scaling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
I&#8217;m rather new to EC2 (and as a result its CloudWatch / Auto Scaling features), so I figured I&#8217;d post about my current thoughts and see if anyone can tell me if I&#8217;m on the right track! I&#8217;m writing everything up as I go, so hopefully it will make a solid blog post for others in the future for going from zero to EC2 + Auto Scaling.<br /><br />Based on my initial research, it looks like the stack will be comprised of:<br /><ul><li>64-bit Maverick AMIs on micro instances, from <a href="http://uec-images.ubuntu.com/releases/10.10/release/">http://uec-images.ubuntu.com/releases/10.10/release/</a></li><li>Puppet for bootstrapping new instances and maintaining existing ones (via the series at <a href="http://ubuntumathiaz.wordpress.com/2010/03/24/using-puppet-in-uecec2-puppet-support-in-ubuntu-images/">http://ubuntumathiaz.wordpress.com/2010/03/24/using-puppet-in-uecec2-puppet-support-in-ubuntu-images/</a>)</li><li>Amazon&#8217;s CloudWatch + Auto Scaling for spinning up/down instances of puppet roles as necessary</li></ul><div>Any yays or nays on this stack? One particular curiosity I had is if Mathiaz&#8217;s guides would be simpler in Maverick, since they were written for Lucid and it seems like each release brings improvements for both EC2/UEC and Puppet. I&#8217;ll also have to figure out how to put some of the roles behind a load balancer, but that&#8217;s for later.</div><div><br /></div><div>Thanks for any suggestions! Once I&#8217;ve got it all figured out I&#8217;ll put up a somewhat comprehensive guide, unless one already exists that I&#8217;ve missed.</div></div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is Intel the answer to Broadcom wireless problems?]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2010/04/26/is-intel-the-answer-to-broadcom-wireless-problems/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2010/04/26/is-intel-the-answer-to-broadcom-wireless-problems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
While I love my Dell XPS 1330 as an Ubuntu laptop, I&#8217;ve been growing quite tired of my Broadcom wireless card that came in it (I swore it had Intel wifi when I bought it). It requires downloading drivers to work (this can lead to a bit of a bootstrapping problem), and seems to frequently drop connections or have issues connecting.<br /><br />I&#8217;m assuming this is due to Broadcom&#8217;s poor drivers, particularly 64-bit (I remember kernel panics and lack of WPA2 in the not-too-distant past), and was assuming an Intel card would clear my problems right up.<br /><br />Has anyone had problems with Broadcom and fixed them by switching to Intel? If so, could you offer any suggestions as to if I might want the Intel 4965, 5100, or 5300 card?<br /><br />Thanks, dear Ubuntu Planet and other readers!</div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Thanks for all the feedback! The consensus definitely seems to be that Intel provides a better experience, so I think I&#39;ll grab a 5300.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Tom Cameron</div>
<div class='content'>
Adding another success story with an Intel A/G/N card. Unfortunately, the Intel drivers do not yet use 802.11n mode.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Mackenzie</div>
<div class='content'>
4965 is nice as long as you&#39;re not on Intrepid (though that may have been fixed since then too).</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
I have a Intel 5300 and it works absolutely superb. Only tested it with 10.04, but everything works out-of-the-box and reception seems very good. AP mode also worked with no extra setup. Packet injection to &quot;test&quot; WEP encryption will work as well with some patches applied.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Alex Wauck</div>
<div class='content'>
Buying a laptop from a Windows-oriented vendor like Dell is always a crapshoot.  The presence of Broadcom wifi is the reason I will not purchase Dell&#39;s otherwise fine Ubuntu machines.  I made sure that my current HP notebook had all Intel hardware when I bought it, but I think I will go with System76 or Zareason next time, if only for personal peace of mind.  Also, it&#39;s nice to get a computer without funding Microsoft.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
I can only confirm your suspicion. My last laptop had broadcom 43something. One year a go I suffered lockups and dropped connections.<br /><br />My current laptop has intel 5100 which is pretty much rocksolid. a plus is that 5100 is capable of wirless-N.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
The Live CD quite happily loads bcmwl-kernel-source off the CD and installs a functional wireless driver.<br /><br />Yet even now, in Ubuntu 10.04, an installed Ubuntu is unable to find and install the same package. Getting a working Broadcom driver seems to require a wired connection, even though a complete package is present on the CD.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
Intel wireless generally works well, but unfortunately it always requires a non-free firmware blob that prevents adding features like AP mode. Fortunately they do have Monitor mode.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Shivan</div>
<div class='content'>
ot my m1330 with intel wireless, no problem.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>nxadm</div>
<div class='content'>
Yes, Broadcom was kind of tricky but it <a href="http://nxadm.wordpress.com/2008/05/21/broadcom-wifi-bcm4312-speedup-on-ubuntu-804-on-a-hp-nc6320-laptop/" rel="nofollow">worked fine</a> at the end.<br /><br />However, when purchasing a laptop myself I made sure that the video and the wifi were Intel. <a href="http://nxadm.wordpress.com/2010/02/09/dell-windows-refund-win/" rel="nofollow">Great choice</a>, as they work out of the box.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>jorge</div>
<div class='content'>
I have one of these with a 4965 and it&#39;s rock solid.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
I have had nothing but trouble with Broadcom cards - even when they work it seems to me they have poorer reception than Intel equivalents.<br /><br />I yanked the Broadcom that came with my M1330 out quickly and replaced it with an Intel 3945 ABG card and it&#39;s been flawless.<br /><br />I recently got a Studio 14Z which came with a Broadcom G-only card (which was the only option, is this 2006?) and it would work for a bit and then totally crash the closed-source driver.  The STA driver worked a bit better, but replacing it with a 5100 AGN card was what really did the trick.  Worked great.<br /><br />Sadly I had to return the 14Z because Dell&#39;s stupid site doesn&#39;t tell you that you don&#39;t get WWAN antennas unless you pop the extra $50 for custom case color, but I&#39;ll likely get another one soon.</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Switched from Ubuntu One back to Dropbox]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2010/02/22/why-i-switched-from-ubuntu-one-back-to-dropbox/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2010/02/22/why-i-switched-from-ubuntu-one-back-to-dropbox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
As many of you surely know, Dropbox and Ubuntu One are applications to keep files on your desktop in sync across multiple computers, and backed up in the cloud. After using Dropbox for a year or so on Ubuntu, the Ubuntu One project came out and I thought I&#8217;d move over to it. I assumed it would be easier to set up, being pre-installed, and could integrate better with the file manager and other applications, being made specifically for Ubuntu.<br /><br />After about 6 months of using Ubuntu One, I found it to be too much of a regression compared to Dropbox and switched back. I thought I&#8217;d detail why here for the usefulness of others and to hopefully provide some constructive criticism to the Ubuntu One team which overall is doing good work. So here&#8217;s why I went back to Dropbox:<br /><br /><b>Better Nautilus integration</b><br />The nautilus (file manager) integration in Dropbox feels very mature and polished. Normally I&#8217;d say this is to be expected since Ubuntu One is much younger, but since the nautilus aspect of Dropbox is open-source, there didn&#8217;t seem to be much of an excuse for the Ubuntu One team to not use it as a starting point or at least as inspiration. Whenever I added files to my Ubuntu One folder, no matter how large or how many, they instantly had the checkbox emblem which implies to me they are in sync, even though they couldn&#8217;t possibly be uploaded that quickly. In Dropbox, the files show an animated progress emblem until they are actually uploaded, and show this again when they are being updated. I wasn&#8217;t able to trust the status of files with Ubuntu One, and that wasn&#8217;t a good feeling.<br /><br />Sharing files in Dropbox is also a lot easier via Nautilus, but that deserves it&#8217;s own point.<br /><br /><b>Easier file sharing</b><br />In my typical use cases of file sharing, I want to go from having a file in mind to someone else seeing that file as quickly as possible, be it in an instant message, chatroom (IRC/Jabber), or email to a friend or two. Dropbox makes this a breeze; drag a file into the &#8220;Public&#8221; folder in your Dropbox directory, and right-click on it and select &#8220;Dropbox > Copy Public Link&#8221;. Now you have a publicly accessible link to your file in your clipboard!<br /><br />I never quite figured out how to do this in Ubuntu One; it seems you have to share files with specific people who also are running Ubuntu One (which really compounds the non-cross-platform issue) via the web interface by typing in an email address. This is a cool idea, but seems way over-engineered as a starting point. This was even brought up at the last UDS in an Ubuntu One session but was brushed off; they sadly seemed more interested in engineering complex sharing UIs than getting feedback to ensure they were solving actual problems.<br /><br /><b>Sane notifications</b><br />I think <a href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntuone-client/+bug/462747">bug 462747</a> is what ultimately drove me to drop Ubuntu One. It notifies you not once but twice for every file you change; once to tell you it is syncing the file and another to tell you it is done. Regarding the first notification, I probably already know that I changed that file; regarding the second, if I&#8217;m really curious about the status of the synchronization, a quick glance at the applet should tell me what I need to know. This was mildly annoying as is, but it does this for hidden files like vim swap files too. Every time I would open or save a file in vim (and I save early and often), I got two notifications about syncing the hidden swap file!<br /><br />Dropbox was much more sane regarding notifications; whenever I would turn on or sit down at a computer, it would show <b>one</b> notification telling me how many files it synced from other machines or, if there was just one changed file, the name of it. Beautiful!<br /><br /><b>Better web UI</b><br />The web user interface for Dropbox felt a lot easier to use, and I often had problems where the Ubuntu One web view would show deleted files or not show files I knew were there that were added days ago. Sometimes I had to collapse and expand a folder a time or two to get it to show the right contents. This led to a similar problem that I mentioned with the nautilus integration; it wasn&#8217;t a UI I could trust to be accurate as was therefore essentially useless. The Dropbox UI was always accurate, and had some nice extras which could prove to be lifesavers like getting past versions of files.<br /><br />I also experienced some other issues including <a href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntuone-client/+bug/498444">bug 498444</a> which caused Ubuntu One applet to start up with the exclamation icon, giving the impression of not syncing files. If I wanted to edit or view a file that might have changed remotely, I had to manually tell the applet to try syncing again after startup to make sure the file was latest version (or else I could silently end up with .u1conflict file, but that&#8217;s another issue). Additionally, although the transparency is praiseworthy, <a href="http://twitter.com/UbuntuOne/status/9498991639">all</a> <a href="http://twitter.com/UbuntuOne/status/9331800792">these</a> <a href="http://twitter.com/UbuntuOne/status/9292086471">tweets</a> <a href="http://twitter.com/UbuntuOne/status/9020860066">about</a> <a href="http://twitter.com/UbuntuOne/status/8963442390">recent</a> <a href="http://twitter.com/UbuntuOne/status/7755587471">issues</a> or <a href="http://twitter.com/UbuntuOne/status/8870678995">downtime</a> do not inspire confidence.<br /><br /><b>That being said</b><br />Ubuntu One does have a few things going for it, however. It is installed by default which means it is the easiest cloud sync/backup solution to get started with for an Ubuntu user. And thanks to CouchDB and a package manager, Ubuntu can ship applications that make it trivial to sync their data with Ubuntu One out of the box. If I can tell all the applications I care about to sync with Ubuntu One (bookmarks, notes, podcasts, basic OS settings/appearance) from one configuration UI, that&#8217;s going to be pretty compelling.<br /><br />While I currently can&#8217;t in good conscience recommend Ubuntu One to a friend (and plenty of my friends don&#8217;t even use Ubuntu), I do have high hopes for the project; it is young and if they can work out some of the above issues, many of them being personal show-stoppers, while providing application and OS integration, Ubuntu One (and perhaps Ubuntu itself) could become too compelling to not use for many people. For now however, Dropbox is the solution which stays out of my way, allows me to solve my problems, and just works.<br /><br />If you are using Ubuntu One or Dropbox, certainly chime in on what the critical features are for you and why you chose one over the other!</div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>iheartubuntu</div>
<div class='content'>
Update: There are now Windows beta versions available of UbuntuOne and UbuntuOne now has a graduated price structure. $2.99 per month for everyone 20GB of space needed or $29 a year. Its working very nice on 10.10 Maverick.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Dan Jones</div>
<div class='content'>
I agree with all your points. I had a similar experience, but I used Ubuntu One even less before I got sick of it.<br /><br />My main problem, though, was lack of cross-platform ability. I don&#39;t only use Ubuntu. I don&#39;t even only use Linux. If Canonical ever ported Ubunutu One to Windows and OS X, I might consider using it again.<br /><br />The proprietary nature of Dropbox does bother me, but then again, I have Flash installed, so how bothered can I really be by it?<br /><br /><br />A note: Dropbox does have other notifications, and they are incredibly useful. If a file changes in your Dropbox on another computer, it shows you a notification when the new file has synced to the one you&#39;re currently using. That&#39;s great for me, because sometimes my home computer might be working on a file in my Dropbox through some cron job, or something, but I&#39;ll be at work (on a Mac), and it&#39;s great to have a little Growl notification saying such-and-such file has changed on Home.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Francesco</div>
<div class='content'>
I was just checking the web to se if others had the same issues with ububtu one as myself&#8230; and found your post.<br />I probably lost a Lazarus project where the sources were under my ubuntu one folder so that I could easily work from different locations (single user) and have the updated version everywhere.<br />Now I found myself sorting out .conflict files manually to try to rebuild the &quot;latest&quot; version.<br /><br />:/</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Hi Nathan! I haven&#39;t tried SugarSync, obviously since there is no Linux version; I use Dropbox to sync 3 Ubuntu computers at the moment :)</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Nathan Brauer</div>
<div class='content'>
Have you tried SugarSync?  I haven&#39;t tried it yet but they seem pretty convincing (see their comparison chart <a href="https://www.sugarsync.com/sync_comparison.html" rel="nofollow">here</a>) compared to DropBox.  They&#39;re on everything but Linux so far though :(</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Eduard</div>
<div class='content'>
I switched from db to u1 because I expected better integration and rather wanted to give my money to canonical. The reliability has steadily improved (I run the daily builds) but all the issues you point out are correct. I have been very disappointed that the service is so inferior to dropbox.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jorge E. Gómez</div>
<div class='content'>
I recently switched to Dropbox as well; my main problem with Ubuntu One were the .conflict files appearing for no valid reason (I was careful to sync before changing between computers, but I always had to double-check and then manually diff the conflict files); that problem is gone since I switched.<br /><br />Lack of symlink support (wishlist #386019) is also a bummer: with Dropbox I don&#39;t have t change the way I work, or where I want my files to be.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>andypiper</div>
<div class='content'>
I have to say that the cross-platform nature of Dropbox is the major win for me. Much as I&#39;d love to be Linux on all devices, fact is I have Windows, Linux and OS X devices (and an iPhone) and Dropbox just works on all of them. I can&#39;t yet see the point of Ubuntu One.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>aaylnx</div>
<div class='content'>
Free account.  I think with the free account there are limitations on how many revisions are stored, but something like 15 or 30 days worth.  I also do my own backup with a Drobo, but for certain docs which I need regularly the web interface comes in real handy.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jef Spaleta</div>
<div class='content'>
Are you a paying DropBox customer now or just using the free account?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>aaylnx</div>
<div class='content'>
It&#39;s been a little while since I&#39;ve used Ubuntu One, but the last time I looked at it you could not revert back to an earlier version of a file or folder the way you can from the Dropbox website.  Is this still the case?  This is a big reason why I&#39;ve not switched from Dropbox yet.  If I mess up a file, or if I accidentally delete it from one machine, I would like the ability to bring it back rather than having those changes propagated to the server and all my other machines as (I think) is currently the case with Ubuntu One.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
Dropbox client is also cross platform (Windows, Mac, Linux, iPhone, and Android coming soon). Right now this is a huge one for me. I only have two Linux machines synced at this point, but what if I wanted to sync a Windows machine with Ubuntu One I&#39;m out of luck.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>desgua</div>
<div class='content'>
I would like to add that Ubuntu One is much slower at least from my city São Paulo, Brazil.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Corey Burger</div>
<div class='content'>
So Ubuntu One is a poor Dropbox clone. Shocking. Now imagine if they had decided to open source the server from day one. That would have bought them marketing time to make the product rock, as opposed to the poor Dropbox clone stories that keep running around.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Thanks for the update Stuart, that&#39;s great to hear! I&#39;ll definitely be following the progress of Ubuntu One and as I hopefully implied I won&#39;t be surprised if (and in fact I hope that) one day I&#39;ll switch back.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Stuart Langridge</div>
<div class='content'>
&quot;I never quite figured out how to do this in Ubuntu One&quot; &#8211; that&#39;s because, right at the moment, you can&#39;t give a file a public URL. This is coming in Lucid &#8211; we&#39;ve been working pretty hard on it since UDS, and it&#39;ll be available with the 10.04 release.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
Ah, so you haven&#39;t suffered connectivity problems then!<br /><br />I frequently find myself where the applet has &quot;disconnect&quot; as the menu item, but the folder has &quot;connect&quot; (which does nothing).  It seems that hibernates and suspends confuse the heck out of everything and nothing short of a reboot fixes it.<br /><br />I&#39;ve also had the case where it most definitively is not connected yet somehow claims that the files are all up to date - something that is not true.<br /><br />There was also a problem where it would keep wanting reauthorization which was allegedly fixed in an update a few weeks ago.  (Each of my machines was listed several times as a result.)<br /><br />My view is that Ubuntu One is at best beta quality whereas Dropbox left beta long ago.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Tom</div>
<div class='content'>
So you hate freedom now? ;)</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[wxBanker 0.7: simple personal finance]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2010/02/07/wxbanker-0-7-simple-personal-finance/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2010/02/07/wxbanker-0-7-simple-personal-finance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Your favorite personal finance application, <a href="https://launchpad.net/wxbanker">wxBanker</a>, has turned 0.7!<br /><br /><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/S29A7hvLBVI/AAAAAAAAAbg/d0PZdNtqyqI/s1600-h/wxBanker-0.7a.png"><img style="display:block; margin:0px auto 10px; text-align:center;cursor:pointer; cursor:hand;width: 400px; height: 247px;" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/S29A7hvLBVI/AAAAAAAAAbg/d0PZdNtqyqI/s400/wxBanker-0.7a.png" border="0" alt=""id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5435634666672162130" /></a><br /><br />This release comes about 2 months after the previous release, and focuses on usability and user experience issues that I obtained from watching people use wxBanker as well as from Launchpad bugs (thanks <a href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/wxbanker/+bug/496878">Arty</a>!). Let&#8217;s take a look at some of the changes, starting with the account control:<br /><br /><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/S28ugG2hSQI/AAAAAAAAAbQ/iIskUB1WYi0/s1600-h/wxbanker-6-7-accountctrl.png"><img style="display:block; margin:0px auto 10px; text-align:center;cursor:pointer; cursor:hand;width: 400px; height: 129px;" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/S28ugG2hSQI/AAAAAAAAAbQ/iIskUB1WYi0/s400/wxbanker-6-7-accountctrl.png" border="0" alt=""id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5435614404389456130" /></a><br /><br />On the right we have the new account chooser in 0.7. The main change is using radio buttons for the accounts instead of links. This is a much better, already understood method for choosing accounts, and will also fit in with themes better. The last item is now &#8220;All accounts&#8221; and is selectable, making it easy to get a view of all your transactions and search in them.<br /><br />The &#8220;Hide zero-balance accounts&#8221; option has moved to the View menu, and now has a keyboard shortcut. I&#8217;ve also removed the total number of accounts from the header, as well as the colons after the account names, to reduce clutter. Finally, everything has been given a bit more padding and the buttons have been slightly rearranged.<br /><br />Additionally, the previous graphing library has been replaced by cairoplot (thanks <a href="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/wxbanker/+spec/replaceable-plot-renderers">Karel</a>!), which looks much more attractive. Let&#8217;s check it out:<br /><br /><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/S286U7l8uqI/AAAAAAAAAbY/ztBe-P27WY4/s1600-h/wxBanker-0.7b.png"><img style="display:block; margin:0px auto 10px; text-align:center;cursor:pointer; cursor:hand;width: 400px; height: 247px;" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/S286U7l8uqI/AAAAAAAAAbY/ztBe-P27WY4/s400/wxBanker-0.7b.png" border="0" alt=""id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5435627406528133794" /></a><br /><br />The Summary view allows you to see a graph of your balance over time, and you can view a graph of a specific account or all accounts by using the account chooser on the left (previously the graph had its own account chooser, that was silly!).<br /><br />And in case you missed the 0.6 announcement, that version brought recurring transactions, XDG directory support, and more intuitive behavior regarding deleting/editing transfer transactions.<br /><br />For downloads and the full list of features and bug-fixes, check out the <a href="https://launchpad.net/wxbanker/0.7/0.7">release page</a>. You can also add <a href="https://launchpad.net/~wxbanker-users/+archive/ppa">the PPA</a> for easy installation and upgrades.<br /><br />If you&#8217;d like to stay in the loop join the <a href="https://launchpad.net/~wxbanker-users">wxBanker Users team</a> (and announcement mailing list) on Launchpad, follow <a href="http://twitter.com/wxbanker">wxBanker on Twitter</a>, or hang out in #wxbanker on irc.freenode.net.</div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Forest</div>
<div class='content'>
I like the message panel idea.  That sounds like a perfect way to do it.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Forest: That seems like a good idea. Can you think of a good way to fit this into the flow without some sort of modal pop-up? What would account creation look like; would this be required or just simpler to do?<br /><br />Maybe using a message panel (as used when creating recurring transactions) to say something like &quot;Your account has been created.&quot; with a button &quot;Add initial balance&quot;, that enables a box an amount field next to it, where you can enter it and it will enter the transaction with date today and description &quot;Initial balance&quot;?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Forest</div>
<div class='content'>
Why don&#39;t you just have it query the user for an initial balance every time they create a new account and then automatically create the transaction representing that initial balance?  This is consistent with the way you&#39;re suggesting users use the program, but also more intuitive.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Hi Anonymous! Once you create the account, just add a transaction representing your initial balance via the controls on the bottom, just like you would in any sort of ledger. Then add transactions from there as they occur!<br /><br />Do you have any suggestions for making this more intuitive? I&#39;d love to hear any of your suggestions!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
haven&#39;t really figured out how, after I create an account, I can set up the current balance of my account&#8230;</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Automating translation template generation and check-ins for Launchpad]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2010/02/02/automating-translation-template-generation-and-check-ins-for-launchpad/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2010/02/02/automating-translation-template-generation-and-check-ins-for-launchpad</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
I <a href="http://mrooney.blogspot.com/2009/07/launchpad-is-now-automatic-magical.html">previously wrote</a> about how excited I was for the automated translation import and export features of Launchpad. Launchpad will automatically notice when you commit a translation template and import it, making it available for translation online. Generous translators will then contribute translations, and Launchpad will commit them back to your project.<br /><br /><img style="display:block; margin:0px auto 10px; text-align:center;cursor:pointer;width: 149px; height: 200px;" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/S2fxD3QRaNI/AAAAAAAAAbI/AfTFW4D9U7s/s400/thumbsup.jpg" border="0" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5433576524119894226" /><br />Okay, so this is pretty good! However for this process to work well, the translation template needs to be generated manually by a developer whenever there are changes to strings. Otherwise, translators are working on potentially outdated strings; some are perhaps not in the application anymore, and there are likely some strings which aren&#8217;t in the template yet.<br /><br />After forgetting to generate and commit my template until shortly before a release more than once (and thus having poor translation coverage on newly added strings), I decided to automate this part of the process as well. All it took was a relatively small script to generate the template, and then if there were any changes, commit and push to the branch configured for automatic import in Launchpad. The following script does just that, by searching for any files using gettext calls starting with _(&#8221; or _(&#8216;, and passing them to xgettext.<br /><br /><pre class="brush: bash"><br />#!/bin/bash<br />set -e<br />ack-grep "_\([\"\']" -l | xargs xgettext --output=wxbanker/po/wxbanker.pot<br />ACTUALCHANGES="`bzr diff | grep \"^[\-\+]msg\" | wc -l`"<br />if [[ "$ACTUALCHANGES" != "0" ]]; then<br />  bzr ci -m "automated generation of translation template"<br />  bzr push :parent<br />fi<br /></pre><br /><br />Note that if you aren&#8217;t using Python, you may need to tweak the regular expression supplied to ack-grep. Once the template is generated, the diff is piped through grep to grab any changes to actual messages and make sure there was at least one. Otherwise there would always be changes due to the timestamp in the template, causing useless commits.<br /><br />I then threw this script into a <a href="http://hudson-ci.org/">Hudson</a> job, the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_integration">Continuous Integration server</a> I use for <a href="https://launchpad.net/wxbanker">wxBanker</a>. I configured this particular job to run nightly, pulling down the latest bzr branch beforehand, and emailing me on any failures.<br /><br />It seems to be working quite well and ensures translators are always translating the latest strings and leaves nothing for me to forget, smoothing out the release process.<br /><br />If this sounds interesting to you but you&#8217;re not familiar with Launchpad as a translation system, check out <a href="http://blog.launchpad.net/general/trying-out-launchpad-translations">http://blog.launchpad.net/general/trying-out-launchpad-translations</a> and feel free to ask any questions here. If you do have experience with translations, how do you handle generating translation templates and then integrating the translations?</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[wxBanker 0.6 preview available, now with recurring transactions!]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/09/20/wxbanker-0-6-preview-available-now-with-recurring-transactions/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/09/20/wxbanker-0-6-preview-available-now-with-recurring-transactions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
I&#8217;ve just released wxBanker 0.5.9 in <a href="https://launchpad.net/~mrooney/+archive/wxbanker-testing">the wxbanker-testing PPA</a>, which is a preview release for 0.6. If you aren&#8217;t familiar with wxBanker already, it is a cross-platform, lightweight personal finance application, and you can find more info at <a href="https://launchpad.net/wxbanker">https://launchpad.net/wxbanker</a>.<br /><br />While there are <a href="https://launchpad.net/wxbanker/+milestone/0.6">many improvements and fixes</a> in 0.6, the main feature is recurring transactions, allowing you to automate repetitive transactions. They are functional in 0.5.9 with one caveat and the purpose of this preview release: there&#8217;s no way (besides sqlitebrowser :) to modify existing recurring transactions. As such I&#8217;d love to get feedback on your impressions of recurring transactions, ideas on a nice configuration UI for them, and of course general feedback. With this I can implement the configuration UI and release 0.6.<br /><br />Here&#8217;s an example of a simple quarterly transaction:<br /><br /><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/Srcm3zebZLI/AAAAAAAAAX4/Ui32D2TBg88/s1600-h/wxbanker-recurring-simple.png"><img style="display:block; margin:0px auto 10px; text-align:center;cursor:pointer; cursor:hand;width: 400px; height: 72px;" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/Srcm3zebZLI/AAAAAAAAAX4/Ui32D2TBg88/s400/wxbanker-recurring-simple.png" border="0" alt=""id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5383814619697210546" /></a><br /><br />and here is a more complex one, with specific days chosen, as well as the transaction being a transfer from another account:<br /><br /><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/Srcl91BFwWI/AAAAAAAAAXw/ANaBFZ7W9PI/s1600-h/wxbanker-recurring.png"><img style="display:block; margin:0px auto 10px; text-align:center;cursor:pointer; cursor:hand;width: 400px; height: 108px;" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/Srcl91BFwWI/AAAAAAAAAXw/ANaBFZ7W9PI/s400/wxbanker-recurring.png" border="0" alt=""id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5383813623678615906" /></a><br /><br />When you start up wxBanker and there is a recurring transaction due, you will see something like:<br /><br /><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/SrcqtaCE55I/AAAAAAAAAYI/FsSU097v09M/s1600-h/Screenshot-wxBanker-1.png"><img style="display:block; margin:0px auto 10px; text-align:center;cursor:pointer; cursor:hand;width: 400px; height: 39px;" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/SrcqtaCE55I/AAAAAAAAAYI/FsSU097v09M/s400/Screenshot-wxBanker-1.png" border="0" alt=""id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5383818839115229074" /></a><br /><br />I didn&#8217;t reinvent recurrence rules but instead (luckily) found the dateutil module for python which includes rrule, an &#8220;implementation of the recurrence rules documented in the <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2445.txt">iCalendar RFC</a>&#8221;, so it should behave quite well.<br /><br />As far as the needed configuration UI goes, there are a couple ideas that I&#8217;ve had so far. Below is the current top-left portion of the UI, for reference:<br /><br /><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/Srco-UL023I/AAAAAAAAAYA/MvdtcqO5lwc/s1600-h/wxbanker-topleft.png"><img style="display:block; margin:0px auto 10px; text-align:center;cursor:pointer; cursor:hand;width: 400px; height: 91px;" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/Srco-UL023I/AAAAAAAAAYA/MvdtcqO5lwc/s400/wxbanker-topleft.png" border="0" alt=""id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5383816930580028274" /></a><br /><br />One idea was to have a third &#8220;Recurring Transactions&#8221; tab after the &#8220;Transactions&#8221; and &#8220;Summary&#8221; tabs, which appears if and only if recurring transactions exist. This would provide a list of recurring transactions and allow editing them via the same UI used for creation, as well as changing the account or removing them altogether. A second idea is to add another button next to the Add/Rename/Remove account buttons in the upper-left, for account configuration (this will be necessary for future features anyway), and allow modifying recurring transactions for that account there.<br /><br />Another perhaps complementary way would be to provide a right-click action on existing transactions which were recurred, for editing. I&#8217;d also like to implement functionality similar to Google Calendar where editing a value on an existing transaction caused by a recurring transaction will ask you if you want to apply that change to just this transaction, all existing, or all future.<br /><br />If you have ideas, please feel free to leave comments here or drop by #wxbanker on irc.freenode.net any time this week after 10AM PDT, to have a more interactive chat about them. <br /><br />Please do let me know what you think from either just the screenshots here or actually playing around with the application!</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Launchpad is now an automatic, magical translation factory!]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/07/30/launchpad-is-now-an-automatic-magical-translation-factory/"/>
    <updated>2009-07-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/07/30/launchpad-is-now-an-automatic-magical-translation-factory</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
I&#8217;ve been using Launchpad to host my personal finance application <a href="https://launchpad.net/wxbanker">wxBanker</a> for a few years now. The thing I was hearing most often was that it wasn&#8217;t localized; people wanted currencies to look the way they should in their country, and the application to be in their language. Let me explain how Launchpad helped me provide translations for my application, and how much of an utterly slothful breeze it has recently become.<br /><br /><img style="display:block; margin:0px auto 10px; text-align:center;cursor:pointer; cursor:hand;width: 320px; height: 148px;" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/SnKYTL6ff1I/AAAAAAAAAT0/DHLdJZYT5nM/s320/slothful.png" border="0" alt="Image courtesy of shirt.woot.com" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5364517561534742354" /><br />Normally to handle translations, an application has to wrap strings with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gettext">gettext</a>, create a template, find translators and give the template to them, collect translation files back, and integrate them into the project. This is painful and is why many applications aren&#8217;t localized, and shut out most of the world as a result. One of the amazing features of Launchpad however, happens to be Rosetta, which brings translators TO your translations via a simple web interface, and then makes those translations available to the developer. With Rosetta, translators don&#8217;t need to understand gettext or translation file formats; they just need to know two languages!<br /><br /><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/SnKLUdixHfI/AAAAAAAAATs/z36K46Y4p3M/s1600-h/ss_rosetta.png"><img style="display:block; margin:0px auto 10px; text-align:center;cursor:pointer; cursor:hand;width: 400px; height: 201px;" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/SnKLUdixHfI/AAAAAAAAATs/z36K46Y4p3M/s400/ss_rosetta.png" border="0" alt=""id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5364503289795780082" /></a><br /><br />So that&#8217;s what a translator sees. Notice how Launchpad even shows how other applications translated the same string. So once you generate a template and upload it, you can assign a translation group to your project such as &#8220;Ubuntu Translators&#8221; so that your strings will be translated by volunteers on the Ubuntu project; if your project isn&#8217;t relevant to the Ubuntu project, you can use the more generic Launchpad Translators group. Now all you have to do is wait for some translations, then download them and check it in to your code. Not too bad, right?<br /><br />It isn&#8217;t, but Launchpad has recently made it so much better. They started by adding an option to <a href="https://help.launchpad.net/Translations/ImportingFromBazaarBranches">automatically import translation templates</a> from your project. This means as you are developing, all you have to do is regenerate the template and commit, and new strings will show up for translators in Rosetta and be translated automatically (from the developer&#8217;s perspective). Then today, <a href="http://blog.launchpad.net/general/exporting-translations-to-a-bazaar-branch">they announced the other side of this</a>, which is automatically committing those translations back into your code on a daily basis. This means that all I have to do is commit templates as I change strings, and Launchpad handles everything else. This is a profound tool for developers.<br /><br />What&#8217;s the next step? Well, from a developer&#8217;s perspective the translation template is a tool to give to the translators or in this case Launchpad. In the future Launchpad could eliminate this by generating the template itself from the code (this is what developers are doing themselves, after all), so that truly all you have to do after you set up the initial i18n/l10n framework is commit code as normal, and Launchpad magically commits back translations.<br /><br />All this work Launchpad is doing gives developers more time to develop while still having localized applications at a very minimal cost. This is continuous translation integration, and boy is it cool!</div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Sneca</div>
<div class='content'>
Hi Michael.<br /><br />Rosetta has gone a long way, and it is a much appreciated tool. However, as a professional translator that sometimes collaborates on free software translations, I must say it is *not yet* a perfect tool. It lacks better concordance support with easier searches, for instance.<br /> I would like to point out that for translating, one needs to know a bit more than just two languages. It is necessary to have a whole lotta of things in mind, and use your brainz in a very complex way :) Whether I do not want to discourage any contributors, l18n is serious business; terminology consistency, some linguistic common sense (and even style) should be stressed. In the business world, bad translations leave bad impressions on your clients. In GNUlinux realmz, where there are quite a few different desktop managers, so many programs and sometimes different names for similar things, bad translations may end up confusing people (esp. newcomers) and eventually turning them, at least, nervous. English prevails largely on the GNULinux world, and the more languages AND the better quality of translations, the closer we will get to squash bug nº1.<br /><br />We will keep on working on it. Cheers!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Thanks for the comment Jeroen! I mentioned Ubuntu Translators because my package is in Ubuntu and it seemed most relevant to readers of my blog on the Ubuntu planet, but mentioning LP Translators for generic use is good to know as well.<br /><br />The problems with automatic translation are definitely true, and it will be interesting to see if any of them can be mitigated. Perhaps allowing someone to import all translations with known good copyrights for untranslated strings, marking them as &quot;Needs Review&quot;.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jeroen Vermeulen</div>
<div class='content'>
Hi, I&#39;m one of the Launchpad Translations developers.  Glad you like the new stuff we built!<br /><br />A very minor point: if you want to invite translations for your project, we now have a Launchpad translation group as well as the Ubuntu translation group.  The Ubuntu group is to focus more on Ubuntu (surprise), whereas the Launchpad group can serve as the &quot;generical&quot; translation group for other projects.<br /><br />And a comment on the &quot;automatically use translations from elsewhere&quot; idea: it&#39;s very tempting, but there are a few obstacles.<br /><br />First, there may be a copyright risk from automatically copying other projects&#39; translations.  And once we automatically start avoiding some translations, there&#39;s a bigger risk of choosing bad translations.<br /><br />Second, not every translation you find will be correct, let alone consistent.  Sometimes people import entire translations to the wrong language!<br /><br />So ideally there should still be a human review step for those suggestions before they definitely go into a project.  And that&#39;s exactly how it works now.  For some programs, the &quot;global suggestions&quot; from other projects let you do a large chunk of the work very quickly, even in languages you only just well enough to see which translations make sense.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Tom, I&#39;m not a Launchpad developer, but I have talk of it before I think.<br /><br />I checked out transifex and it seems pretty interesting. I know LP has done work in the past to make Rosetta easier to use for upstreams and sync the two, and I am sure it will only get easier and better.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Tom</div>
<div class='content'>
I love the &quot;Automatically use suggestions for otherwise untranslated strings&quot; option, will it come? Launchpad should get a big language model like Google Wave that would certainly help. Maybe Mark should hire some cheap Google engineers ;)<br /><br />It would be cool if Rosetta could work directly with upstream as http://transifex.org/ can. That also would be a cool addition for people who prefer git etc.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Thanks simpsus :) The tagging branch is waiting on some work from the author, as well as some conceptual work I need to do (how can tagging be hidden/out of the way for users who don&#39;t need that, but easy to discover and turn on?) I&#39;d like to get 0.6 by the end of August with recurring transactions and perhaps reporting (https://launchpad.net/wxbanker/+milestone/0.6), and target tagging/categories for 0.7 not much later.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Tom, that could be cool and I wouldn&#39;t mind an &quot;Automatically use suggestions for otherwise untranslated strings&quot; checkbox, but there are going to be a bunch of previously untranslated strings that will still need translation by a person. And for short phrases there can be multiple translations. For example, the word &quot;read&quot; in English can be both a verb and an adjective, and &quot;import&quot; can be a verb and noun. In another language there might be two different words for each use though, and only a person with context (provided by translation comments) can know which one to use. Certainly though, it seems like it could help you grab some low-hanging translation fruit that&#39;s better than nothing.<br /><br />As far as your second question, I&#39;m not sure what you mean by &quot;hosted&quot;. If the project isn&#39;t registered on Launchpad at all, it can&#39;t use Launchpad features obviously. But there is nothing stopping a project hosted anywhere from creating a Launchpad account and using it for Rosetta. If the code is hosted elsewhere (and Launchpad allows you to specify external SCMs and bug trackers, as well as import from them) you could still have a branch in Launchpad solely for Launchpad to import and export from, and handle merges back and forth on your end yourself.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>simpsus_science</div>
<div class='content'>
Hi Michael,<br />nice to see you give wxBanker some publicity. Are there any news when the transactions tagging and advanced categories will be merged? When is the 0.6 release planned? <br /><br />Cheers<br /><br />Simpsus</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Tom</div>
<div class='content'>
Couldn&#39;t it automatically translate without users? Just take the most used strings from other apps?<br /><br />And how about projects that are not hosted on LP?</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simple timing of Python code]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/07/06/simple-timing-of-python-code/"/>
    <updated>2009-07-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/07/06/simple-timing-of-python-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Often when I am writing in Python, I find that I want to see how long a particular function call or set of statements are taking to execute.  Let&#8217;s say I have the following code that gets executed frequently:<br /><pre><br />for i in range(10000000):<br />   x = 934.12 ** 32.61 * i / 453.12 ** 0.23<br /></pre><br />and I want to know how long it takes to execute to see if it is slowing down my app and should be optimized. Previously I would surround it as such:<br /><pre><br />import time; x = time.time()<br />for i in range(10000000):<br />   x = 934.12 ** 32.61 * i / 453.12 ** 0.23<br />print time.time() - x<br /></pre><br />This will print out the duration in seconds of that code segment, but is more work and typing than I want, and more cleaning up later. I realized that the new &#8220;with&#8221; statement in Python could probably help me out. Let&#8217;s create a little timer class that cooperates with it:<br /><pre><br />class Timer():<br />   def __enter__(self): self.start = time.time()<br />   def __exit__(self, *args): print time.time() - self.start<br /></pre><br />Now all we have to do is:<br /><pre><br />with Timer():<br />   for i in range(1000000):<br />       x = 934.12 ** 32.61 * i / 453.12 ** 0.23<br /></pre><br />You can also try:<br /><pre><br />with Timer():<br />   time.sleep(1.5)<br /></pre><br /><br />For these, 0.28738 and 1.50169 are what I get, respectively. While something like this couldn&#8217;t really replace application-wide profiling via <a href="http://docs.python.org/library/profile.html">a module like cProfile</a>, it can be an extremely useful and quick way to see if your prototype is scalable or not. I usually end up having a debug.py or helpers.py file in my larger projects with little tools like this, and I&#8217;ll probably end up adding this one as well.<br /><br />Let me know if you are doing something similar, or if I&#8217;ve reinvented something that already exists. I&#8217;d also love to hear from people profiling their python code and what techniques they are using, as I am just starting to learn about it.</div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>flimm</div>
<div class='content'>
Got here after reading wxbanker&#39;s source code. You&#39;re right, it does look handy.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>mgedmin</div>
<div class='content'>
Using the with statement for this is a brilliant idea!<br /><br />Check out <a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/profilehooks" rel="nofollow">profilehooks</a> on PyPI for something like this at function level, implemented using decorators.  I wonder how difficult it would be to have the same object (or function) act both as a decorator and as a context manager.<br /><br />Timeit is a great module, but it serves a different purpose: very accurate microbenchmarks.  Sometimes you just need to know whether a for loop takes 1 or 20 seconds; repeating that for loop 1000 times to get its accurate speed up to the nearest microsecond is overkill.  Plus, timeit&#39;s API is cumbersome and inconvenient, or at least I can never remember offhand how to use it, which is the same thing in my book.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Paddy3118</div>
<div class='content'>
&#8230; The timeit module documentation states that it stops you repeating some common errors when doing this kind of task.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Thanks liw.fi for pointing that out, I wasn&#39;t aware of it! However while convenient, I don&#39;t think it is as trivially injectable into existing code paths. It looks great for testing a function or one-liner, but not for a random segment of code that might be a part of a large function / sequence.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>liw.fi</div>
<div class='content'>
See also the timeit module in the standard library.</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Karmic Desktop UDS run-down!]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/05/31/karmic-desktop-uds-run-down/"/>
    <updated>2009-05-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/05/31/karmic-desktop-uds-run-down</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
I just got back from a wonderful UDS in beautiful Barcelona and thought I would provide a summary of what we can expect in the Karmic Koala 9.10 desktop. Keep in mind that I don&#8217;t speak for Canonical and what follows is just my understanding of what is on the table for Karmic.<br /><br />Overall it is gearing up to be a pretty radical and exciting release; there are some changes to the default application set as well as some major version upgrades of existing core components. We are trying to be fairly aggressive in terms of new stuff so that if Canonical wants Karmic+1 to be an LTS (Long Term Support) release, we can have fairly stabilized new technologies by then (thanks to 6 months of stabilization in the Karmic cycle)  instead of having to wait until after the LTS (Karmic+2) to introduce them. Since many of these changes would be too radical to first appear in an LTS, if we don&#8217;t upgrade now we may not be able to for a year, and have to maintain old versions for 3-5 years in the LTS.<br /><br />On the messaging front, Ekiga will be dropped from the CD to save 10 megs, and Empathy will likely replace Pidgin due to a responsive upstream, voice/video support, and better GNOME integration. It also now has the ability to import accounts from Pidgin, so this should help out with migration. I checked it out a bit at UDS and was impressed with how useful it is with absolutely zero configuration. It will pull your name from the system and enable avahi (auto-discovery of people nearby, like bonjour) with no set up, which made it quite easy to get in contact with people at the conference. You can also supply your email and Jabber ID to the avahi interface to allow other people to discover that info as well.<br /><br />It also sounds likely that Banshee will replace Rhythmbox as the default media player, and it is the official default of UNR (Ubuntu Netbook Remix) Karmic. This will bring a snazzier interface, better device support including iPods and Androids, and quite importantly an active and responsive upstream. I will admit to not being a huge fan of this transition for Karmic as it seemed too early for me (the lack of a folder watch is quite a regression for me, and it has been promised for the last 3 releases or so, so I&#8217;m not holding my breath), but after checking out 1.5 for a bit I will admit that it is growing on me. The user interface does seem nicer, and the lightweight video library which keeps track of what you haven&#8217;t watched is nice. However, it does seem to use 3-10x more memory than RB which is very troubling (60-300MB compared to RBs fairly consistent 25MB), especially on the netbook scene. I&#8217;ve also had issues with it skipping occasionally, which is very unfortunate. Hopefully the UNR switch will put pressure on better memory management for Banshee.<br /><br /><div style="text-align: center;"><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/SiNywNSLPuI/AAAAAAAAALw/auGXRwC9KH0/s1600-h/banshee-slide-device-overview.png"><img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 320px; height: 234px;" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/SiNywNSLPuI/AAAAAAAAALw/auGXRwC9KH0/s320/banshee-slide-device-overview.png" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5342239755516722914" border="0" /></a>Banshee syncing with an Android G1<br /></div><br />Empathy and Banshee will probably replace their predecessors around alpha 2 of Karmic, and will be either left as default or reverted based on reported regressions and bugs. Keep in mind that if you end up not preferring these applications, the other ones still exist and you can continue to use them.<br /><br />There are also going to be a bunch of underlying speed improvements, with the boot speed goal being 10-12 seconds. When Ubuntu talks about boot times, we are referring to the time from when grub starts (when Linux first gets control of the machine) to when the user is at a fully loaded desktop with no I/O. The main test machines being used by Canonical here are Dell Mini 9s, with auto-login enabled to get a consistent log-in time. This is pretty impressive as the boot goal was 25 seconds in Jaunty, which was met, and was aggressive itself as Intrepid booted in about 65 seconds on the Dell Mini 9.<br /><br />grub2 is likely to be default for new installations (upgrades will have grub1 chainloaded to grub2), with ext4 as the default filesystem. The boot process will also be streamlined, with the grub timeout set to 0 and the boot menu hidden. There will instead be two new ways to boot into a different system now. First, there will be a key that can be pressed while booting to bring up an OS chooser, which will halt the current boot and restart into the chosen one. Another goal is to have the restart menu item in GNOME aware of installed OSes and allow the choice there, so you could select for example &#8220;Restart into OSX&#8221;. All in all this means no racing to select the OS for dual-booters, and a faster boot process as well. /tmp is also hopefully going to be made a tmpfs, which means it will reside in RAM and overflow to a swapfile (which in recent Linuxes have on par performance with swap partitions). This means power savings, less disk I/O (especially great for SSDs), and of course blazingly fast performance which should help out a lot especially when, say, loading files from inside an archive The Gnome Display Manager (GDM, which handles the login screen) will also likely be upgraded to GDM2.<br /><br />Finally let me fire off a few more changes. Power management is being improved all around, with one change already landed being that audio cards will be automatically powered down after 10 seconds of no sound. Encrypted Home directories will hopefully be easier to set up now with an option right in the graphical installer, and I&#8217;m working on a UI for managing this and encrypted Private directories in Karmic, more on that later. Firefox 3.5 should be the default version of Firefox. For notifications which want to display actions if the user is interested, there is work on morphing windows:<br /><br /><div style="text-align: center;"><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/SiNyWBN1JGI/AAAAAAAAALo/xTaOTOUafdU/s1600-h/morphing-window.png"><img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 320px; height: 121px;" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/SiNyWBN1JGI/AAAAAAAAALo/xTaOTOUafdU/s320/morphing-window.png" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5342239305600672866" border="0" /></a>Source: <a href="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/NotificationDesignGuidelines">https://wiki.ubuntu.com/NotificationDesignGuidelines</a></div><br />Ubuntu is also working on being social from the start (see desktop-karmic-social-from-the-start on gobby.ubuntu.com), perhaps installing Gwibber by default and asking the user if they want to integrate social sites (twitter, facebook) into the desktop when they visit them in Firefox, via an extension. There has also been work in looking for <a href="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+spec/desktop-karmic-gnomescan">a better scanning application to replace xsane</a> (perhaps GnomeScan), some look into using Gnome Control Center, and a common printing dialog.<br /><br />Okay phew, that&#8217;s what I&#8217;ve got to report! Let me know what you think of these decisions and changes, and if there is anything you were hoping for that didn&#8217;t make it, or really anything else you&#8217;ve got to say!</div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>News Blog</div>
<div class='content'>
Nice Post<br /><a href="http://www.thewinesocietyofindia.com/wine-blogs/steven/" rel="nofollow">Steven Spurrier</a></div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Regarding the last anonymous post, I&#39;m not even sure if you read my post. KMS support IS planned for the next release, and I specifically mentioned it. Delta updates were also discussed at the summit as well.<br /><br />Since Ubuntu and Fedora have different release schedules, they are going to have differences as different technologies and features mature at different times. Both distributions have had certain features before the other and that is surely the way it will continue.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
what a boring release it will be&#8230;<br />app1 changed to app2&#8230;<br />ubuntu is really getting years behind fedora:<br />- no multiseat (MDM) support<br />- no delta updates<br />- no smooth loading (KMS) support<br />and it&#39;s not even planned&#8230; dispite the fact that some of these features were requested for years!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
&quot;Ekiga will be dropped from the CD to save 10 megs&quot;<br /><br />why not save lots of megs by leaving out mono/banshee/tomboy?<br /><br />there&#39;s gnote to replace tomboy, and banshee doesnt appear to be fully functional..</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
Banshee? Mono fail!<br /><br />Empathy has no UI for dialing out on voice calls, doesn&#39;t have metacontacts, and its SIP and IRC support are underdeveloped. I&#39;ve been tracking development and testing it for years. It&#39;s still crap for usability, though I understand it&#39;s an abstraction-obsessed programmer&#39;s wet dream.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>The Mad Hatter</div>
<div class='content'>
We don&#39;t use VLC for legal reasons. The same reasons apply to Mono applications. Mono needs to be purged from Ubuntu, along with the applications that use it (FSpot, Tomboy, Banshee). This will also save a considerable amount of disk space.<br /><br />I would also suggest changing out Evolution for Thunderbird. The amount of integration between Evolution and the Gnome Desktop environment reminds me to much of the way Internet Exploder is integrated into Windows, and the problems caused by that.<br /><br />As a final note, I think that we should consider not using any software which isn&#39;t GPL/BSD/MIT/Apache/Mozilla licensed. License proliferation is becoming a serious issue, which can lock code from reuse. The above licenses are (at least in my opinion) the best ones from a point of sharing.tr</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
Agreed with the above poster not thrilled with Banshee on two counts: 1) it is not nearly as lean as RB, which is quite a snazzy app in of itself, and 2) it is encumbered by .NET and Mono infested. I think it would be good for the distro&#8217;s to heed R. Stallman&#8217;s advice and stick to GNU applications, and if closed source must be included make sure its from a originator without a history of exploits of such.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Blimundus</div>
<div class='content'>
Thanks for the run-down! These are very interesting developments to hear about.<br /><br />I am particularly interested in the debate on the scanning application.<br /><br />Etienne&#8217;s work on GnomeScan started off with the right design choices, and with the goal to make scanning as ubiquitous as printing. In other words, as I understand it, GnomeScan is all about integration with other programs, the file chooser etc&#8230; I think it would be great to see this becoming a reality.<br /><br />GnomeScan would benefit from Gnome/Ubuntu giving it some attention though.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Bayger</div>
<div class='content'>
Michael: I have added a blueprint for the idea suggested by me. It&#8217;s called desktop-karmic-color-themes. I don&#8217;t know what to do next with this. This is my first blueprint. I don&#8217;t even know if this is the usual place to post such ideas.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jeffrey Seguerra</div>
<div class='content'>
I read lot of rants about mono&#8230; was mono discussed in Karmic UDS?<br /><br />http://tinyurl.com/pycr9u</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jef Spaleta</div>
<div class='content'>
You had sessions at UDS about gnome 3.0&#8230;but is Canonical talking directly with upstream about integrating Canonical built technologies like libindicate? <br /><br />UDS is a walled garden. Don&#8217;t misintepret talking &#8220;amongst yourselves&#8221; as a substitute for discussion with upstream. <br /><br />Packagekit adoption would be an example. packagekit-gnome is a gnome module now. It&#8217;s moving along a path towards deep integration into the GNOME desktop.  How much work has Canonical invested release after release into refining its distro-specific update manager experience? How much of that manpower expenditure work is directly working against adoption of PackageKit as a common cross-desktop solution? <br /><br />PackageKit adoption has originally brought up for intrepid UDS.  I&#8217;m not holding my breath for Karmic. Especially in light of the AppCenter proposal which is an even more aggressive divergence path than the current gnome-app-install tool.<br />https://wiki.ubuntu.com/AppCenter</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Alexander, I think there was a PackageKit session, I&#8217;d check summit.ubuntu.com and look at the schedules. If there is one it should be linked to a blueprint / wiki page.<br /><br />Jef, what you are pointing out is definitely true. If we diverge too much and upstream stops maintaining what we are patching, we are either left maintaining it ourselves or porting it, either of which is extra manpower as you say and is suboptimal. We are looking long term and there were some sessions at UDS on GNOME 3.0, Shell, Zeitgeist, Control Center and such. The plan is to have as many GNOME 3.0 components as possible easily installable in Karmic, and solicit some early feedback on user experience, regressions, and integration with other Ubuntu aspects.<br /><br />There is definitely some exciting work going on to make it really easy to use the latest upstream versions of packages in future Ubuntus, which should really help upstreams get better feedback from us and make development upstream easier as well. Plus it should eliminate some surprises by pointing out integration issues early.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jef Spaleta</div>
<div class='content'>
Do you know if upstream gdm has incorporated the presence functionality Canonical introduced in Intrepid? Is Canonical going to forward port that or is essentially duplicating functionality in the gdm trunk with a custom implementation? <br /><br />The differentiated guest and presence features that Canonical developed against the 2.20 codebase was one of the reasons holding back from using gnome 2.26 in Jaunty. And it appears to be something Canonical is going to continue to spend manpower on.<br /><br />You have to be careful, the more you differentiate and rely on those differentiated features, the harder it is for you to continue to move forward as upstrem executes its own feature roadmap.  The fact that Canonical is having to spend time refactoring its customized guest session and customized fast-user-session code..code that was created against the older 2.20 gdm codebase..means Canonical has less manpower resources to help finish off the gdm rewrite.  <br /><br />And looking even longer term, how much of the differentiated work that Canonical is doing across the Gnome desktop more generally is going to make it into the vision for Gnome 3.0? Is all the effort that continues to go into making libindicate and notify-osd work across the application space going to be incorporated into what gnome 3.0 is? Will it even fit in with gnome 3.0 concept of a shell interface?  How much is Canonical engaged in upstream roadmapping for new functionality?  You can&#8217;t really argue an &#8220;agree to disagree&#8221; attitude if Canonical isn&#8217;t taking part in the roadmapping discussion and making the case for integration of their technology implementations.  <br /><br />-jef</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
kubuntu has packagekit now, so i imagine there is at least SOME work being put into it</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Alexander</div>
<div class='content'>
Any news on integrating PackageKit as the principal software installation mechanism?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Thanks for reminding me of that feathertail. I didn&#8217;t follow that too much but the blueprint is here: https://blueprints.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+spec/desktop-karmic-integrating-with-ubuntu-one . The plan is to make it as easy to use as possible (and potentially integrate into migration-assistant if you already have it) without being invasive such as popping anything up or adding an unconditional step to the installer. The client is not proprietary, it is open-source and in fact I have already used the source to help me in another project so I am quite grateful for it!<br /><br />Jef, that is a great question. I am not an authority on this topic (you might try dbarth and seb128?) but my understanding is we want the bleeding edge of GDM, so definitely 2.26, I assume 2.28. Since that is the case it should be easy to upstream, but whether we are doing the work upstream or downstream I don&#8217;t know. Upstream is the preferred approach so I imagine if upstream wants this feature, we would. Ubuntu gets knocked for doing too much work downstream and while some of this is deserved (there was in fact a general session on this), in some cases upstream is not interested in our direction, and that is the purpose of being a different distro after all. If we weren&#8217;t doing anything different there wouldn&#8217;t be a point to existing!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jef Spaleta</div>
<div class='content'>
What version of gdm is Canonical committed to shipping in Karmic?<br /><br />Jaunty is still shipping the gdm 2.20 release while the last upstream release was gdm 2.26.<br />http://ftp.acc.umu.se/pub/GNOME/sources/gdm/<br /><br />Is the restart option for gdm going to be developed against gdm upstream trunk in collaboration with upstream gdm? Or is it going to be a downstream patch built against the old gdm that Ubuntu ships like some of the previous gdm patchset that Canonical developed in the Intrepid development time period?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>feathertail</div>
<div class='content'>
What about the Ubuntu One integration that I have been hearing about? And if it&#8217;s being included, isn&#8217;t that kind of distressing when it&#8217;s proprietary?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Anonymous, upstream GNOME isn&#8217;t switching to Banshee as far as I know (but Banshee would eventually like them to) but as andreasn points out below (thanks!), apparently GNOME doesn&#8217;t ship one at all except totem. So this isn&#8217;t a divergence from upstream, just a change on the Ubuntu side. And in fact going to Empathy is in fact a convergence bringing us closer to GNOME! As far as upstreaming the boot stuff, last I heard (last UDS) Debian was not interested due to how wide-reaching the changes are, but maybe they&#8217;ll come around. This also could have changed recently.<br /><br />nailor, you can find the blueprint at https://blueprints.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+spec/desktop-karmic-gnomescan. I&#8217;ll add this to the post.<br /><br />gilir, I agree and that was one of the first things I noticed as well that was disappointing about Banshee; no fade in/out.<br /><br />Alex, I think Mono is more modern and should allow easier extensibility and maintenance as well as make new contributors more likely. Plus tomboy and gnome-do are already using it. As far as PackageKit goes, I&#8217;m not sure, but you can check out summit.ubuntu.com for the full schedule!<br /><br />Mackenzie, thanks for the info and I have heard that, but I doubt that a custom widget takes THAT much more memory; something else is definitely going on. Plus, my library is about 50 gigs and 8,000 songs, so I feel like I am on the upper end of the average desktop user anyway. I don&#8217;t think we should be harming the experience of people with libraries of this size, so someone can have 220GB of music with less problems :) I&#8217;ve also had issues with it skipping on my Core 2 Duo, which RB never does, so that is unfortunate. That said, I do think Banshee is headed in a cool direction and I&#8217;m excited to see where it goes.<br /><br />Bayger, I don&#8217;t know of that being considered but it could be cool; I&#8217;d personally love for a &#8220;look and feel&#8221; choice in the installer which lets you enable a dock instead of a bottom gnome-panel as well.<br /><br />Pro, the idea with boot choice is to make it fairly simple (I think pressing something like shift/alt/ctrl) and make it as discoverable as possible, but with Windows or OSX you just &#8220;have to know&#8221; so we don&#8217;t have much to go by as far as presenting this. Also, the restart option should make it fairly easy.<br /><br />Pēteris, I&#8217;m up in the air about some of the changes as well, but we&#8217;ll see how feedback goes. If upstream is as responsive and interested as claimed, the kinks should be worked out. And indeed, gnomescan does seem to be what is being considered.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Pēteris Krišjānis</div>
<div class='content'>
Pidgin replacement - good, RB replacement - bad, for scanning - Gnome Scan please. Everything else sound good :)</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Pro</div>
<div class='content'>
The new boot menu which makes grub time set to 0 might cause a headache for new users to ubuntu who are just trying it and would like to have easy access to their win/osx os also.<br />it seems this step needs to be executed really well for it to be good for both experienced and new uwsers.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
Great news indeed! Thanks for your report.<br />It seems that Karmic will be awesome.<br /><br />(Even if I don&#8217;t feel completely trustworthy Banshee for Mono&#8230;)<br /><br />@Bayger<br />Usually I keep the brown colour but I like your idea.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>andreasn</div>
<div class='content'>
Nice to hear Banshee is moving closer to getting included. The player have a really good and slick UI, and hopefully it means we can convert more people to Ubuntu.<br /><br />Anonymous: GNOME upstream don&#8217;t have a default music player included in the desktop module set [1] (unless you count Totem)<br /><br />1. http://live.gnome.org/TwoPointTwentyfive/Desktop</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Bayger</div>
<div class='content'>
Great news! By the way, have you considered adding desktop theme selection during installation of Ubuntu 9.10? I am sure that a lot of people would be very grateful to have a choice between standard brownish theme and 2 or 3 other colour schemes (green, blue). This would be great option, especially for beginers. And yes, people are a little bored of all those browns everywhere.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Mackenzie</div>
<div class='content'>
Banshee has a higher memory overhead as a baseline, but it does not require more memory for larger libraries the way Rhythmbox does.  This is due to a Banshee-only widget which only needs to store the visible items in the song/album/artist list plus 10 above and 10 below.  Rhythmbox&#8217;s stock GTK list viewer must hold ALL items, so if you have a very large library, it could easily use hundreds of megs of RAM.<br /><br />If RB consistently uses 25MB for you, you must have a small library.  For people like my friend with 219GB of music, RB uses much, much more.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Alex Eftimie</div>
<div class='content'>
I don&#8217;t like the idea of Banshee either, mostly because of .NET implications.<br /><br />Anything else sounds great!<br /><br />How about PackageKit integration? Have you discussed that?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>gilir</div>
<div class='content'>
Banshee lacks also the gapless/crossfading playback, which is a NO-GO for me. Sure Banshee have cool features, but it should not hide the problems Banshee have (memory, crash, slow &#8230;).<br />Also RB is not so inactive, the 0.12.2 was released some days ago and there are 2 GSOC on RB.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>nailor</div>
<div class='content'>
Michael, can you provide a pointer to more info about the ongoing investigation of scanning applications?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
Is GNOME upstream switching to banshee too?<br /><br />I hope you push those speed improvements back to Debian.</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A teaser: Desktop integration with encrypted directories for Karmic]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/05/14/a-teaser-desktop-integration-with-encrypted-directories-for-karmic/"/>
    <updated>2009-05-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/05/14/a-teaser-desktop-integration-with-encrypted-directories-for-karmic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Recently I&#8217;ve been working on <a href="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+spec/ecryptfs-desktop-ui">desktop integration with ecryptfs</a>. <a href="http://blog.dustinkirkland.com/">Dustin Kirkland</a> has done some awesome work enabling encrypted Private directories, as well as entirely encrypted Home directories, and I want to bring a UI to that goodness for the Karmic desktop.<br /><br />UbuntuOne displays a banner at the top of its shares, and this inspired me to borrow the code for use with encrypted Private directories. After a bunch of hacking and debugging, I finally got something to show up:<br /><br /><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/SgvK9e86AJI/AAAAAAAAAKw/BqYg9C1Z_iU/s1600-h/nautilus-encrypted.png"><img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 320px; height: 221px;" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/SgvK9e86AJI/AAAAAAAAAKw/BqYg9C1Z_iU/s320/nautilus-encrypted.png" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5335581341179838610" border="0" /></a><br />Pretty exciting! There is much work to be done behind the scenes but this is an encouraging start. After I get this working I plan on making a UI for installing ecryptfs-utils (the necessary package), setting up an encrypted Private directory, and managing/configuring one (or an encrypted Home). This UI would perhaps be available from System -> Administration -> Encrypted Directories, and would allow a user to have a directory of encrypted files available in a few clicks, which is mounted/unmounted transparently at login/logout.<br /><br />What do you think? Are you currently using an encrypted Home or Private directory? Would you be more likely to if there was a UI to set it up? Please share your thoughts and comments :) I&#8217;ll be at UDS and can schedule a session on this if there is interest, as well.</div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Perpetual</div>
<div class='content'>
Hi, I really need something like this. My family multimedia center, based on ubuntu, contains a lot of movies (horror and such) that my small children better not click on by accident. Still, I want them to be able to access the cartoons section in the Movies directory. Everybody just uses my account, it is always logged in, so decrypt at login does not cut it. Instead I need something that pops up an &#8220;enter decrypt password&#8221; dialog when someone tries to access the grown-up movies.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Since I got some upstream questions I&#8217;ll give an update there. The projects this would touch are ecryptfs-utils and potentially seahorse. ecryptfs-utils has stated an interest in this so that means the nautilus extension, python API, and setup/configuration UI are likely to land upstream there.<br /><br />As far as seahorse I haven&#8217;t heard anything (I think I contacted them but am not sure), but I&#8217;ll hopefully meet someone involved in that project at UDS and discuss it with them. Perhaps I&#8217;ll end up putting an &#8220;Encrypted Directories&#8221; tab in that utility which allows the installation of ecryptfs-utils and from there allows you to launch the ecryptfs UI. I don&#8217;t think embedding a whole UI devoted entirely to ecryptfs makes that much sense in seahorse.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>gourgi</div>
<div class='content'>
i really like this approach!<br />nautilus intergration looks very cool!<br />As for the menu approach, i strongly believe that you should talk/work in collaboration with upstream (seahorse?) before implementing yet another system-&gt; administration menu item. Encryption and keyrings  is the right way to go IMHO&#8230;<br /><br />Looking forward to have this in karmic! <br />Gourgi</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
What about implementing this nice feature upstream?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Wirelizard</div>
<div class='content'>
I love the fact that the open-sourced UbuntuOne client has already help produce cool improvements like this.<br /><br />All the closed-source UbuntuOne server software has produced in the same timeframe is controversy in the community!<br /><br />Go open source!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Nathan Nutter</div>
<div class='content'>
A UI is definitely necessary if desktop users are to take advantage of it. On Mac OS X there is FileVault and it is super easy to setup. However, I don&#8217;t currently use it because of concerns of stability/corruption. Of course, I have no evidence of this it&#8217;s just something that got baked into my head. I think it&#8217;s important to address the &#8220;safety&#8221; of using a new feature and I hope Canonical/Ubuntu will have some information about using encrypted home folders and/or encrypted directories.<br /><br />Things like:<br />* How do I know some &#8220;minor&#8221; corruption won&#8217;t end up locking me out of all my data?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Thanks for all the encouraging comments everyone!<br /><br />meastp, for 2-factor encryption with a USB stick I&#39;ll point you to Dustin&#39;s post on how to do exactly what you say! http://blog.dustinkirkland.com/2009/03/ubuntu-encrypted-home-with-2-factor.html<br /><br />wiflye81, the theme is shiki-colors (wise) available on gnome-look and potentially will be added to the community themes package in Karmic.<br /><br />Jim, I am not doing any graphical work for other desktop environments but I have created a python API for ecryptfs and a generic controller for my UI which other DEs can leverage to implement their equivalent quite easily. I&#39;ll probably be talking about this at UDS.<br /><br />Philipp, filename encryption is supported since Jaunty and is the default, though you can specify to not encrypt filenames if you like.<br /><br />Andrew, System -&gt; Preferences does make sense in some ways, and ideally it would be a tab in the Encryption and Keyrings entry there, although that application is done in C++ and Glade, neither of which I am familiar with so I am not sure it will end up there. I suggested Administration simply because it is a somewhat advanced feature, and will lead to data loss if you forget your password. Though ideally this risk can be mitigated with the proper prompts to record your encryption passphrase.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Andrew</div>
<div class='content'>
Would System &gt; Preferences not be better, as it is on a per user basis, rather than a system wide thing.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Dread Knight</div>
<div class='content'>
I will use encryption for sure with a GUI. :) Keep up the good work!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Philipp Kern</div>
<div class='content'>
Are filenames encrypted nowadays?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Philipp Kern</div>
<div class='content'>
This comment has been removed by the author.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Alan</div>
<div class='content'>
An excellent development, but one which I might not end up using.<br /><br />Reason being - I need to share an encrypted local space with Windows machines on the same network (&amp; a MacBook possible soon &#8230;).  I can (and have for some time) do this with TrueCrypt, although with less desktop integration.<br /><br />So my ideal would be integrated AND Truecrypt compatible.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jim</div>
<div class='content'>
Hi There,<br /><br />Thanks for doing this work. :) If possible, would any of this desktop integration be available for Kubuntu or Xubuntu? <br /><br />Per this bug ( https://bugs.launchpad.net/ecryptfs/+bug/365796 ), the ecryptfs functionality was a bit less fleshed-out in Ubuntu&#8217;s non-GNOME distros for Jaunty, so it would be good to include Kubuntu and Xubuntu folks on this. <br /><br />Thanks again!<br /><br />Jim</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>wiflye81</div>
<div class='content'>
Great work, love to see it in karmic.<br /><br />Is this the official new theme for karmic (green looks good for koala and eucalyptus ;)) ?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jeff</div>
<div class='content'>
+1 for the GUI to set up encrypted directories!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>MadsRH</div>
<div class='content'>
Currently I&#8217;m not using encrypted directories, but would be more likely to if there was a slick UI to set it up.<br /><br />Fantastic work :-)</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jon Dowland</div>
<div class='content'>
I think encrypted-home-by-default for installs is a good goal to reach for. This is the first I&#8217;ve heard of ecryptfs though and I wonder if it&#8217;s the best tech for the job. I currently use libpam-mount and dm-crypt/luks.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>clivew</div>
<div class='content'>
Excellent concept<br />Love to see it in Karmic<br /><br />Best of luck!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
I am really looking forward to using this, especially since the new laws came in in the states saying that when you (re)enter the states they can take any paper or electronic storage device from you for &#8220;examination&#8221; without any kind of warrant or even suspicion of wrongdoing?! I mean, I have nothing illegal to hide (not even ripped music or movies) but I would prefer customs officials weren&#8217;t looking at my private documents and photos without me knowing. If they need to ask for a password, they need to give an explanation as to why they want it. :)<br /><br />Anyway, I&#8217;m very grateful for your work on this, as the only thing holding me back from using an encrypted directory is a) not knowing how without a gui and b) just wanting to know it&#8217;s stable first.<br /><br />Given a little time, b. will take care of itself, so I&#8217;m very happy to see work on a nice gui!<br /><br />Thank you!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>meastp</div>
<div class='content'>
I would love this!<br /><br />I used encrypted fs a couple of cycles ago, but it was a hassle to have to type the password on start up. Since I am using a laptop, I would like to encrypt at least some of my data, in case of theft etc. This solution will make a breeze, it seems! :)<br /><br />Could you perhaps consider a feature for two-phase security (e.g passphrase-thing on a usb-pen ) on login / unlock ?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
Great, i would love it. <br />Kind of EncFSVault wich replaces Apple&#8217;s FileVault with good encryption. <br />Hope to see this soon</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Counting the number of Ubuntu users]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/05/06/counting-the-number-of-ubuntu-users/"/>
    <updated>2009-05-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/05/06/counting-the-number-of-ubuntu-users</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
There have been a few <a href="http://blogs.computerworld.com/how_many_desktop_linux_users">articles</a> recently trying to estimate the number of Linux users, which is apparently a challenging problem. However I have to wonder why it can&#8217;t be figured out at least at the distro level by simply storing hashes of IP addresses that hit Canonical&#8217;s update site, and looking at the number of unique ones each week/month.<br /><br />There are going to be people using mirrors, but this is a small percent to lose to at least get something in the right magnitude, and the most popular mirrors could probably do a similar thing and contribute their numbers anyway. The only other main drawback would be multiple Ubuntu machines under the same IP, which again seems like it would only result in a slight inaccuracy. You&#8217;d also lose a small percent to users infrequently using their computers such that they aren&#8217;t updated on a monthly basis, but yearly results would pull back in any of these people using their computers frequently enough to warrant counting.<br /><br />Alternatively, as others have suggested as well, if Google would just release their numbers for browsers hitting google.com, we&#8217;d probably have a solid idea as well.<br /><br />Are there already accurate numbers for Ubuntu and if not, am I missing something with my proposal?<br /><br />UPDATE: Jef pointed out that Fedora is already doing this at http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Statistics#Yum_Data, which is pretty awesome! That shows about 14 million unique repository connections, so making a VERY rough, not remotely scientific estimate, we could use distrowatch to estimate that Ubuntu has 1.68 times the number of users as Fedora, and get something around the order of 24 million users that have connected.</div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>silver</div>
<div class='content'>
What about universities, schools and companies using ubuntu all under the same ip-address?. This could have a pretty big influence on the numbers!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Tommi</div>
<div class='content'>
I would either count at all the Distrowatch site. Even the sites admin says that should not be used anyway to calculate the amounts of users.<br /><br />And I would like to see too that MAC address is hashed to upgrades, but Fedora is already using the smolt what generates unique ID of the system specs and sends it to Fedora. Sadly (good thing) it is not default so not all enable it. But by those figures says that Fedora has more installs than Ubuntu. Sorry about that, you ain&#8217;t special, only gaining the media attention ;-)<br /><br />I dont think that market share figures means anything for us. (OK, mayby some like to extend their virtual penis). <br /><br />We all - what ever distribution we use - are using same OS. It does not matter what is your opinion about system, packagemanager, brand or even freedom. All we use Linux OS to power all the other software. Without Linux, we would not be here. So kudos to Linus Torvalds to code the OS in first place and kudos for Richard Stallman to start GNU project what gave us GPL and so on free software and we got the Linux OS licended under it (GPLv2).<br /><br />I see more other distributions than Ubuntu in Finland, (the homeland of the Linux OS). Same thing around on the European or Asia where I have traveled.<br />Ubuntu has smaller share on technical oriented users (science labs, computer stores, universities etc) but that does not matter at all. We are all using same OS, the Linux (kernel)!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>scottritchie</div>
<div class='content'>
If you want a rough estimate for the proportion of Ubuntu vs Fedora users, a better back-of-the-envelope would be the Desktop Linux Survey: http://www.desktoplinux.com/cgi-bin/survey/survey.cgi?view=archive&amp;id=0813200712407<br /><br />Now, it&#39;s 2 years out of date, but back then Fedora had 6% and Ubuntu 30%; if that&#39;s still the case today this would put Ubuntu at 5 times Fedora rather than 1.68 times Fedora.<br /><br />Another metric might be Google Trends: http://www.google.com/trends?q=fedora%2C+ubuntu  &#8211; suggests that the Ubuntu:Fedora ratio of searches has been increasing; so either the ratio of usage has been changing or Ubuntu users are becoming even more likely to search for Ubuntu for some reason.<br /><br />Now, Google Trends and Desktop Linux surveys can be inaccurate for a variety of reasons.  I&#39;ll note, however, that the google trends data is consistent with the desktop Linux survey data; both imply roughly 5x - and both are doubtlessly better proxies for usage share than distro watch.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jef Spaleta</div>
<div class='content'>
Micheal:<br />At no point did I say that all &#8220;fun&#8221; things can&#8217;t be &#8220;meaningful.&#8221;<br /><br />What I said was very specific. The distrowatch metric is not meaningful. The google trends metric is not meaningful. I making absolutely no claim about the meaningfulness of any other &#8220;fun&#8221; activity. I will say that making global maps of client connections to MirrorManager using GeoIP is both &#8220;fun for me&#8221; and &#8220;meaningiful&#8221; as it gives Fedora an easy to understand snapshot of how globally used Fedora is. <br /><br />You&#8217;ve extrapolated what i said and attempted to apply beyond the bounds of the original context. Is that &#8220;fun&#8221; for you as well..making gross generalization about what other people say? That&#8217;s neither friendly nor healthy. You want to keep this friendly..you want to keep this constructive? Then take more care and rein in your tendency to generalize.<br /><br />I find it really amazing that you can so easily discount accurate ShipIt numbers as a useful rough metric and yet&#8230; you reached for distrowatch as a scaling metric.  Stop putting the cart before the horse. Make accuracy the primary importance.. then worry about interpretation. Don&#8217;t waste your time trying to interpret the meaning of numbers that aren&#8217;t even accurate measure.<br /><br />If LoCos have hundreds of cds collecting dust every release&#8230;that&#8217;s also something you could get accurate stats on&#8230;you just have to survey LoCos and ask them.  if they are requesting CDs and not giving them out..that is a drain on Canonical resources. It benefits everyone by making sure that&#8217;s not happening too much.<br /><br />-jef</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Anonymous, hashing the MAC addresses instead is a pretty good idea! I just suggested IPs because that is something the mirrors already have access to so it wouldn&#8217;t involve any extra data sending or controversy. It is a great idea though, it would fix the cases of multiple users behind one IP, and also one user one multiple IPs.<br /><br />soren, it sounds like you are right, sorry :) The more I look into this, the more I see that mirrors are more common than I thought. Thanks for enlightening me and sharing your knowledge! Though, I still think it would be feasible if enough mirrors participated. Combined with hashed MAC addresses, it has a decent accuracy potential.<br /><br />Jef, ShipIt is certainly countable but I am not convinced how useful it would be. Surely some people order CDs and never use them, and someone in a shop might order one and install it a hundred times. And each LoCo could have hundreds on hand that never get used. Also, I&#8217;m not sure I could agree that something which is fun can have no meaning; fun IS meaning!<br /><br />Lots of knowledgeable people have shared great stuff here, so that&#8217;s awesome! Let&#8217;s just try to keep it friendly and healthy :)</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jef Spaleta</div>
<div class='content'>
Are you suggesting that Shipit is uncountable?  It most certainly is countable. If anything its the most accurate statistic you have available to you. <br /><br />Canonical could tell us tomorrow exactly the number of ShipIt disks they have paid for AND the number of disks purchased directly for the Canonical shop. Have they ever done that? Have they ever put any hard numbers out with regard to how active ShipIt is? I haven&#8217;t found them. If they haven&#8217;t that&#8217;s a pretty remarkable lack of transparency. <br /><br />How about you press your leadership to publish the no-guesswork numbers associated with the amount of media sent via ShipIt for Intrepid on a monthly basis since the release of Intrepid.  What is it maybe 1% of the total number of Ubuntu users Canonical employees have publicly claimed exist? <br /><br />You want to haggle over a statistic that below the noise floor of any overall estimate fine..go right ahead&#8230;noise seems to be pretty important for Ubuntu supporters&#8230;much more than accuracy.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>soren</div>
<div class='content'>
Michael, I know what &#8220;order of magnitude&#8221; means, and I&#8217;d be <I>deeply</I> surprised if people using archive.ubunut.com as their mirror wasn&#8217;t the minority. We have an extensive mirror network, and we configure Ubuntu systems be default to use country specific mirrors. Hence, metrics based on web requests to the primary archive mirror at archive.ubuntu.com would be completely useless to even come close to the order of magnitude of users. The only thing you can use it for is to get a rough idea about trends, but even then, it&#8217;s a stretch.<br /><br />Jef, you&#8217;re missing the fact that Ubuntu is freely available from ShipIt, no matter where in the world you are, and no matter what sort of network connectivity you have (as long as you can actually get to ShipIt, of course). Hence, users who can only get Linux by these means will never be counted by a service such as MirrorManager. Since a similar service to ShipIt does not (to my knowledge) exist for any other Linux distro, number from MirrorManager-like services will be biased in favour of non-Ubuntu distros. Let&#8217;s face it: There&#8217;s no way to get hard numbers for number of Linux installs.<br /><br />I&#8217;m sure there&#8217;s also organisations that for whatever reason do not want to publish their use of Linux at all, even to an (alleged) anonymous service like MirrorManager. I don&#8217;t say &#8220;alleged&#8221; because I don&#8217;t believe it to be anonymous, but because there&#8217;s no way for me to know whether that&#8217;s the case or not, and for some organisations, that&#8217;s simply not good enough.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
Couldn&#8217;t apt send the MAC-address (or some hash of it) to some kind of MirrorManager-like service? You would then get unique machines and I don&#8217;t think people would feel it would violate their privacy (I don&#8217;t feel my MAC-address is something private)&#8230;</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jef Spaleta</div>
<div class='content'>
I&#8217;m offended.. because those are exactly the sort of numbers which the laypress picks up on. By doing the calculation and publishing a calculation you know has no merit..you are not helping make the case for solid methodology for counting that can be reused by all distros..so we can get good solid numbers out to the press. Because god knows the press don&#8217;t care about accuracy.<br /><br />Do you want solid numbers or not for total linux usage? If you do, then don&#8217;t publish goofball numbers yourself. <br /><br />distrowatch and google trends&#8230;while &#8220;fun&#8221; to look at..have no meaning..have no value..in any well understood sense. You might as well just generate random numbers between 1 and 10 million for all distros and call them a rough estimate with a +/- 9 million errorbar on all the numbers.<br /><br />MirrorManager and the statistics it generates is a methodological approach that everyone can use..we could get solid consistent numbers across pretty much all linux distributions if they adopted the MirrorManager approach to handing out mirror information to clients dynamically.  There&#8217;s real value for everyone in this tech. Users, network admins, and distributors.  We don&#8217;t have to rely on CEO&#8217;s making up deployment numbers in press interviews. <br /><br />-jef</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Jef, I completely agree! That&#8217;s why I said it was &#8220;a VERY rough, not remotely scientific estimate&#8221;. It was just meant as a fun number. I am not at all serious about it; I thought it would be obvious from my disclaimer. Obviously the ratio obtained on distrowatch is flawed in numerous ways. I&#8217;m sorry if I have offended you by multiplying some numbers together :) If you really don&#8217;t think my disclaimer was sufficient, feel free to let me know why it isn&#8217;t VERY rough or not remotely scientific, and I can adjust it.<br /><br />pfrields, thanks for leaving a comment! It is good to hear that you guys are somewhat serious about metrics like this, and are certainly quite ahead of Ubuntu (as far as I can tell) in terms of collecting the data and being open about it. Like Jef said, it is certainly an aspect that is missing from Canonical/Ubuntu which is unfortunate considering their other marketing efforts.<br /><br />Anyway I definitely appreciate some Fedora folks chiming in here and didn&#8217;t mean to offend anyone with my wild extrapolations.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jef Spaleta</div>
<div class='content'>
Your distrowatch metric is absolute crap.  I refuse to let that stand without comment. <br /><br />Xandros is ranked pretty low.. and yet it has a significant number of pre-installs via being the linux Asus uses on its EEE netbooks&#8230;for like what is it now 2 whole years. In fact from netbook sales estimates Xandros is crushing Ubuntu netbook pre-installs.<br /><br />In no way whatsoever can you reasonably argue that the distrowatch metric correctly places Xandros compared to the 30 or so other distros in front of it. No way. <br /><br />The distrowatch scaling metric does not stand up to scrutiny.<br /><br />To understand how to use the distrowatch metric you have to understand why people are going to distrowatch. You also have to understand that distrowatch&#8217;s own ranking system has a nonlinear affect on the ranking. Higher ranked distros are going to get more interests from new distrowatch visitors..because they are highly ranked.  It&#8217;s a feedback loop in the methodology. And it makes for an absolutely crap metric of anything at all.    <br /><br />If you are serious about this you need to find a metric that actually measures what you are interested in. <br /><br />What you need to do is demand Shuttleworth or any other Canonical employee who has so far been quoting userbase numbers in the press for the last 3 years..that they actually describe how they get those numbers.<br /><br />http://www.theregister.co.uk/2008/10/27/shuttleworth_ubuntu_commitment/<br />&#8220;Precise Ubuntu installed base numbers are impossible to obtain, but Shuttleworth said the most recent estimate is about 8 million users for the Linux variant. Ubuntu does not have any call-home features to help Canonical count installations. That&#8217;s because Shuttleworth does not want to violate users&#8217; privacy or put up any barriers to adoption for the software. &#8220;We actually have no idea,&#8221; Shuttleworth admitted.&#8221;<br /><br />Numbers have contexts&#8230; methodology has meaning. You can&#8217;t just make up numbers and scaling factors just because they seem to fit the argument you are making. You have to test them for sanity. The distrowatch scaling factor is not a sane metric.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>pfrields</div>
<div class='content'>
I do look at total uniqueness once in a while.  As with all the measurement scenarios, there are some flaws &#8211; the office I used to work in had many users on different versions, but they would be counted as one IP address since they were behind a firewall.  And if the object is to capture number of *machine* installations, then you&#8217;re also missing users who have more than one version on separate machines at home (as I do).<br /><br />Nevertheless, the count I just found from the already collected IP lists was over 12.5 million totally unique IP addresses, out of around 14 million current IP addresses found through simple summing.  Obviously this count doesn&#8217;t include Fedora derivatives such as CentOS, Scientific Linux, Red Hat Enterprise Linux, and so on.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Anonymous, I am familiar with popcon but that is a purely opt-in system so as such is only useful for relative comparisons between packages, not for getting a good count.<br /><br />PriceChild, using the security repo seems like a good idea, although it appears that for me I am hitting my mirror for security too. Some users/admins probably disable everything but that anyway.<br /><br />Jef, that is awesome, thanks for the resource! Do you know if the total across versions is unique across them? That is, if I have Fedora 9 installed and then upgrade to Fedora 10, do I get counted twice? That seems like a common place where people are going to get double counted over the course of a year.<br /><br />pochu, hopefully getting the main and US repository picks up a large percentage, and making it easy for the other mirrors to participate would make it fairly accurate.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>pochu</div>
<div class='content'>
IIRC the installer sets apt to use mirrors by default, so people using the canonical repo are likely the minority</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jef Spaleta</div>
<div class='content'>
What you mean you don&#8217;t trust Canonical&#8217;s statement has been using every year since 2006 that Ubuntu has 8 million users?  I don&#8217;t trust it either.<br /><br />Fedora already has a way to estimate users via IP.  We have the dynamic MirrorManager service..and it has logs&#8230;<br /><br />http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Statistics#Yum_Data<br /><br />People have put a lot of thought in to what is actually achievable and what is not with regard to Fedora metrics:<br />http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Infrastructure/Metrics<br /><br />There&#8217;s absolutely no reason Canonical couldn&#8217;t take the MirrorManager codebase and adapt it for Ubuntu&#8217;s needs. Unlike Canonical, which spends a lot of time building closed web services codebases they are reluctant to share. All of Fedora infrastructure is done in the open..including the MirrorManager service.  <br /><br /><br />MirrorManager is important enough to talk more about. Every Fedora client by default contacts the MirrorManager service asking for which mirrors to use. The MirrorManager service even lets admins on large private networks redirect fedora clients in their network block to a local private mirror..without client reconfiguration. We still count those clients because they contact MirrorManager instead of having to be manually reconfigured to point to the local mirror.  Our MirrorManager service is a benefit to both the user and the local network admin who is trying to conserve bandwidth&#8230;.and its enabled by default.<br /><br /><br />-jef</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>PriceChild</div>
<div class='content'>
perhaps those hitting the security repo (central, not mirrored and used by default unless sa chooses not to) could be used&#8230; infact I&#8217;m pretty sure they&#8217;ve looked at that before.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
You know that http://popcon.ubuntu.com/ exists?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
soren, it doesn&#8217;t quite sound like you understand orders of magnitude if I understand your comment correctly. Unless people using the default mirror are in the MINORITY (I highly, highly doubt this is the case), it would easily be on the same order. And second, as I mentioned in the post, the most popular mirrors would likely contribute their counts to Canonical as well, making it irrelevant.<br /><br />Stefano, I agree, but again this number would be better than throwing around download numbers and random guesses. And conversely to your point, as Drew mentions, there are going to be users on netbooks/laptops updating from many different IPs which will partially offset that issue.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Stefano</div>
<div class='content'>
Yes,<br />  counting unique IPs is the first whing that can be done, but clearly this is not accurate due to NAT.<br /><br />Behind a single IP you might have N users, and you don&#8217;t know how many they are.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>soren</div>
<div class='content'>
I think you&#8217;re greatly underestimating the percentage of users using mirrors. I don&#8217;t think we&#8217;d be anywhere near the order of magnitude of users that way.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Drew Stephens</div>
<div class='content'>
This sounds like good idea to me - each distribution&#8217;s package repositories (well, except for Red Hat/Fedora with it&#8217;s decidedly lack-luster and ill-used repos) has a good handle on the number of actively used machines.  There will be some that won&#8217;t get counted, because they update from someone&#8217;s local mirror, and a few that will get counted multiple times when the check form different IPs, but it should be a close-enough number.</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Extending Java’s Semaphore to Allow Dynamic Resizing]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/04/20/extending-java-s-semaphore-to-allow-dynamic-resizing/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/04/20/extending-java-s-semaphore-to-allow-dynamic-resizing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<a href="http://eng.genius.com/blog/2009/04/20/javas-semaphore-resizing/">Marshall wrote an excellent post</a> explaining how to dynamically change the number of permits when using semaphores in Java, which I thought I&#8217;d share for anyone interested. This can be particularly useful if you have a long-running daemon which you don&#8217;t wish to restart for changes such as this. If you are using semaphores in Java, or if you don&#8217;t even use Java but just want to learn more about semaphores, I&#8217;d recommend <a href="http://eng.genius.com/blog/2009/04/20/javas-semaphore-resizing/">giving it a read</a>.</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Email Deliverability & RFC 2142: Everything you wanted to know and never dared to ask]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/04/13/email-deliverability-rfc-2142-everything-you-wanted-to-know-and-never-dared-to-ask/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/04/13/email-deliverability-rfc-2142-everything-you-wanted-to-know-and-never-dared-to-ask</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Today <a href="http://eng.genius.com/blog/2009/04/13/rfc2142-deliverability/">Franck Martin wrote an interesting post</a> regarding <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2142">RFC 2142</a> (&#8220;Mailbox names for common services, roles and functions&#8221;) and how it relates to email deliverability. If you are running your own email server or own a domain, you may interested in reading it as it sums up what email addresses are expected to be manned at any domain and for what purposes.<br /><br />For example, did you know that &#8220;if an Internet service provider’s domain name is COMPANY.COM, then the ABUSE@COMPANY.COM address must be valid and supported&#8221;? And are you manning your postmaster and hostmaster addresses?</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Genius.com is Eagerly Anticipating PHP 5.3]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/04/08/genius-com-is-eagerly-anticipating-php-5-3/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/04/08/genius-com-is-eagerly-anticipating-php-5-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Over at the Genius Engineering blog we just put up<a href="http://eng.genius.com/blog/2009/04/08/eagerly-anticipating-php-53/"> a post regarding our anticipation of PHP 5.3</a> and what we are looking forward to in it. We&#8217;d love to get some feedback and thoughts on it, and hear what other people are interested in regarding PHP 5.3 that we may have missed. If you&#8217;ve been following PHP 5.3, or haven&#8217;t and want to catch up, <a href="http://eng.genius.com/blog/2009/04/08/eagerly-anticipating-php-53/">check it out</a>!</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[wxBanker 0.5 RC available for testing and translating!]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/04/06/wxbanker-0-5-rc-available-for-testing-and-translating/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/04/06/wxbanker-0-5-rc-available-for-testing-and-translating</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Recently I&#8217;ve been hard at work on the next version of wxBanker, a lightweight personal finance application, and would like to get out the 0.5 release candidate for testing and <a href="https://translations.launchpad.net/wxbanker">translations</a>. To check it out, add my <a href="https://launchpad.net/%7Emrooney/+archive/wxbanker-testing">wxbanker-testing PPA</a>. It also runs on Windows and OSX (albeit less tested), so feel free to grab the <a href="https://launchpad.net/wxbanker/0.5/0.5">source tarball</a> (it&#8217;s python, so no compilation necessary) and then check out the included README. The only hard dependency is wxpython, although installing numpy and the simplejson library for python allow for graphing and csv importing respectively.<br /><br /><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/Sdr39pxUU0I/AAAAAAAAAJc/qB3skDFi5rc/s1600-h/Screenshot-2.png"><img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 320px; height: 108px;" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/Sdr39pxUU0I/AAAAAAAAAJc/qB3skDFi5rc/s320/Screenshot-2.png" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5321838548248449858" border="0" /></a><br />wxBanker 0.5 has been a long time in the making, as it represents a large refactor of the underlying code to make everything much faster, more stable, and easier to extend and implement new functionality. This is especially noticeable in the start up time.<br /><br />There is also a new transaction grid which allows for sorting, a CSV import option in Tools (so you can import transactions from your banks initially)<br /><br /><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/Sdr0YzHl5CI/AAAAAAAAAI8/itA1mNudySc/s1600-h/csvimport.png"><img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 320px; height: 315px;" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/Sdr0YzHl5CI/AAAAAAAAAI8/itA1mNudySc/s320/csvimport.png" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5321834616567751714" border="0" /></a><br />&#8230;and enhanced right-click actions for transactions which now work on multiple selected transactions:<br /><br /><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/Sdr1YGSCBBI/AAAAAAAAAJE/1-1YyM9V6I4/s1600-h/rightclick.png"><img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 320px; height: 130px;" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/Sdr1YGSCBBI/AAAAAAAAAJE/1-1YyM9V6I4/s320/rightclick.png" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5321835704043570194" border="0" /></a><br />See the included changelog for a full list of new things. Launchpad is also fairly well integrated into wxBanker, so to file a bug or do almost anything else, just use the help menu. The Spanish and French translations are complete but I could really use help everywhere else: <a href="https://translations.launchpad.net/wxbanker">https://translations.launchpad.net/wxbanker</a> !<br /><br /><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/Sdr2AI-8l-I/AAAAAAAAAJU/_-Il8uV5otQ/s1600-h/helpmenu.png"><img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 218px; height: 161px;" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_HU7L5oFDSeA/Sdr2AI-8l-I/AAAAAAAAAJU/_-Il8uV5otQ/s320/helpmenu.png" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5321836391963596770" border="0" /></a><br />Check out <a href="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/wxBanker">https://wiki.ubuntu.com/wxBanker</a> for more screenshots, or the wxBanker homepage at<a href="https://launchpad.net/wxbanker"> https://launchpad.net/wxbanker</a> for more information including the users team/mailing list, and the translations team. If you are interested in the less exciting stable version, 0.4.1.0 can be found in the Ubuntu repos as of Jaunty, available in about 18 languages.<br /><br />Enjoy, and let me know of any issues or comments you have, and thanks in advance for translations :)</div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
I figured out the problem with the import errors. In the file wxbanker.py, before the import of wx, wx.aui, just add the line: import wxversion; wxversion.ensureMinimal(&quot;2.8&quot;)<br /><br />This way even if wxPython 2.6 is the default on your system, as long as you have 2.8 or better it will use that install for wxBanker.<br /><br />A fix for this has been applied and it should work fine out of the box in the upcoming 0.6 release.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
Paul &amp; Cilla, hello !<br /><br />I had the same pb on my Ubuntu Jaunty after installing PyKaraoke because it installed wxpyton 2.6 and I have already 2.8.9.1 so when you have many versions in python, it take the older so it&#39;s why after unistalling wxpython 2.6 (and so PyKaraoke) it&#39;s works fine. So try to find in Synaptic if you have many versions of Wxpython and try out to unistall all of them except 2.8&gt; , but only if not important software you use are depending to them. And normally it have to works instantanly.<br /><br />But i&#39;m not a python expert and if there is a solution or a workaround to have many versions of wxpython (and python himself too) working together without conflict, i&#39;m interrested.<br /><br />So good luck and bye !!<br /><br />PS : to developpers, I&#39;m  forced to say you that multiplatform and easy developpement is not only through WxWidget+Python : Try out QtCreator !! Ok, it&#39;s C++, but it&#39;s so easy, flexible and powerfull, and portable too ! And the software produced is quite more speedy. And you have also an intergrated UI designer which is marvellous. I said that because I discovered it 2 month ago and I have already developed so many project with it so quickly that I can&#39;t stop to talk about it to other developpers because to be really franch, I don&#39;t love python  at all :( &#8230;.  It think it is buggy, slow and not very flexible. And for this reason, i&#39;ve started to transcode many Python programs ins C++ to speed-up them (DJL, Alacarte, Elisa, Gnome-packagekit &#8230;&#8230;). So on these ideas I leave you at your tasks. But very good program ! Thanx.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
Hi Paul and Cilla, thanks for trying it out! That is usually the error that you get if your version of wxPython is too old; wxBanker requires at least 2.8.8.0. Do you know what version you have? You can find out by running python from a command line and then typing &#8220;import wx; wx.version()&#8221;. Also, what OS is this? I would try getting the latest version from www.wxpython.org .</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Paul &amp; Cilla&#39;s Place</div>
<div class='content'>
I ran your apt-get install script and tried to run banker. I got this error:<BR/>./wxbanker.py<BR/>Traceback (most recent call last):<BR/>  File &quot;./wxbanker.py&quot;, line 24, in (it says module, but that isn&#39;t allowed in your blog) &lt;    module   &gt;<BR/>    import wx, wx.aui<BR/>ImportError: No module named aui</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>crashsystems</div>
<div class='content'>
One feature I think is rather important is export to CSV. I was bored this evening, so to amuse myself I whipped up a little module to do just that. I pushed <A HREF="https://code.edge.launchpad.net/~crashsystems/wxbanker/csvexport" REL="nofollow">my branch</A> to launchpad, so feel free to use it if you think it will be useful. I don&#8217;t have any experience with wxWidgets yet (I&#8217;ve mostly worked with GTK), so I did not write any GUI stuff for this feature. If you don&#8217;t beat me to it, I may get around to doing that one of these days.<BR/><BR/>Keep up the great work!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Cláudio Novais</div>
<div class='content'>
Hi Michael,<BR/><BR/>I&#8217;m translating to Portuguese and it&#8217;s almost completed!<BR/><BR/>You are doing a great work, keep going!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
@crashsystems: I think the scope of the application is appropriate for personal and small business finance, at least for the bookkeeping aspects. If there is anything that you find it is missing, I will be happy to implement it as I would like to support small business use as well. Nice print reporting of accounts should be coming in about a month which I imagine is useful. Try it and let me know what it needs!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>crashsystems</div>
<div class='content'>
This program looks very interesting. Do you think it would be suitable for a small business that has no need for payroll related features?</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael</div>
<div class='content'>
@1: In the first screenshot I am using Dust, now included in Ubuntu as of Jaunty. The other two are Shiki-Colors (Wise).<BR/><BR/>@2: Phil, I am familiar with the term wanker, though didn&#8217;t know banker was synonymous. I don&#8217;t really see it is a problem but I will consider any names someone throws out; do you have a suggestion?<BR/><BR/>@3: Thanks for the feedback, that&#8217;s what I am going for!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
Dutch translation finished :-)<BR/><BR/>Great program btw, much more clear than gnucash or similar<BR/><BR/>keep up the good work!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Phil</div>
<div class='content'>
Is the name significant and fixed? Banker is sometimes used in the UK (esp SE England) as a euphamism for wanker (it derives from the old London tradition of rhyming slang) Adding wx in front just makes it worse!</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Anonymous</div>
<div class='content'>
looks great. What gnome theme are you using, btw?</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using the "finally" block in Python to write robust applications]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/02/25/using-the-finally-block-in-python-to-write-robust-applications/"/>
    <updated>2009-02-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/02/25/using-the-finally-block-in-python-to-write-robust-applications</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
This is the first post in my series of three on using XMLRPC to run tests remotely in python (such as javascript and selenium tests in web browsers) and get the results. If that doesn&#8217;t concern you, this post is probably still relevant; I&#8217;d just like to cover the groundwork of making code that is stable and repeatable even in the face of [un]expected problems. Luckily for us, python has a wonderful &#8220;finally&#8221; block which can be used to properly clean up or &#8220;finish&#8221; regardless of Bad Things. Let&#8217;s look at an example of a common problem this can solve:<br /><br /><span style="font-family:courier new;"></span><blockquote><span style="font-family:courier new;">getLock()</span><br /><span style="font-family:courier new;">doStuff()</span><br /><span style="font-family:courier new;">releaseLock()</span></blockquote><br /><br />We need exclusive access to a resource, so we get a lock. We do some stuff, and then release the lock. The problem is that if doStuff raises an exception, the lock never gets released, and your application can be in a broken state. You want to release the lock no matter what. So what you should do is:<br /><br /><span style="font-family:courier new;"></span><blockquote><span style="font-family:courier new;">getLock()</span><br /><span style="font-family:courier new;">try:</span><br /><span style="font-family:courier new;">    </span><span style="font-family:courier new;"></span><span style="font-family:courier new;">&nbsp;&nbsp;doStuff()</span><br /><span style="font-family:courier new;">finally:</span><br /><span style="font-family:courier new;">&nbsp;&nbsp;releaseLock()</span></blockquote><br /><br />Now save a SIGKILL, the lock is going to be released. This is pretty basic, but it is impressive how robust the finally block is. You can &#8220;return&#8221; in the try block or even &#8220;sys.exit()&#8221; and the code in the finally block will still be executed.<br /><br />I recently used this with XMLRPC to safely tell the remote machine to clean up if the local script ran into problems or even got a SIGTERM from a keyboard interrupt. Here&#8217;s a more elaborate example:<br /><br /><blockquote style="font-family: courier new;">proxy = xmlrpclib.ServerProxy(remoteIP)<br />try:<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;result = proxy.RunTests()<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;if result is None:<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;sys.exit(1)<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;else:<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;return result<br />except:<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;sys.exit(2)<br />finally:<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;proxy.CloseFirefox()</blockquote><br /><br />The remote machine (&#8220;proxy&#8221;) is running some tests in firefox. While it does this it sets a lock so no one else can run the same tests. If something goes wrong, this lock needs to be reset and firefox needs to be closed so they can run again later. If it gets a result, return it. If it doesn&#8217;t or something goes wrong, we still clean up but now we can exit with an error code. One of the neatest things about this for me was Ctrl+C&#8217;ing the script on my computer and watching the remote machine cleanly quit firefox and release the lock for another process to use.<br /><br />This is great whenever you need to put something in a temporary state, or change the state after an operation no matter what happens. Think of locks, temporary files, memory usage, or open connections where it is important to close them. Conversely however, make sure you DON&#8217;T use an approach like when it isn&#8217;t appropriate.<br /><blockquote><br /><span style="font-family: courier new;">for client in clientsToPing[:]:</span><br /><span style="font-family: courier new;">&nbsp;&nbsp;try:</span><br /><span style="font-family: courier new;">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;ping(client)</span><br /><span style="font-family: courier new;">&nbsp;&nbsp;finally:</span><br /><span style="font-family: courier new;">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;clientsToPing.remove(client</span>)</blockquote><br /><br />This is potentially incorrect behavior, because if you failed to ping your client you may want to keep it on the list to try again next time. However, you also may only want to attempt this once and then the above approach would be correct!<br /><br />In my next post I am going to turn more specifically to remote browser testing and explain how exactly to set up both ends of the connection. After that I&#8217;ll finish by making a post on using twisted + SSL to retrieve posted results over HTTPS.</div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>imnobukowski</div>
<div class='content'>
Unfortunately, there are quite a few exceptions that can happen *between* bytecodes. The most commonly encountered is KeyboardInterrupt but there are others. That means this code:<BR/><BR/>f = open(&#8216;blah.txt&#8217;, &#8216;w&#8217;)<BR/>try:<BR/>  &#8230;<BR/>finally:<BR/>  f.close()<BR/><BR/>doesn&#8217;t always close the file. You could have an exception between open and the start of your try&#8230;finally block! Yay python.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Marius Gedminas</div>
<div class='content'>
If you like try&#8230;finally, you&#8217;re going to love <A HREF="http://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0343/" REL="nofollow">the &#8216;with&#8217; statement</A>.<BR/><BR/>I do.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Dennis K.</div>
<div class='content'>
Look at python 2.5&#8217;s context managers and the with statement. These are a more elegant way of solving this very problem without littering your code with finally: statements.</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ensuring that you test what your users use]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/02/23/ensuring-that-you-test-what-your-users-use/"/>
    <updated>2009-02-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrooney.github.com/blog/2009/02/23/ensuring-that-you-test-what-your-users-use</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Recently I&#8217;ve come across two pitfalls when testing one of my python applications. In two different cases the tests will run fine in my checkout, but fail miserably for anyone else (because the application is broken). What was happening?<br /><br />1) I had a new file which is required to run, but I forget to &#8216;vcs add&#8217; it. Because the file existed in my sandbox, everything was well. But no one else was getting this file, so they couldn&#8217;t even run the application. This one is somewhat easy to detect because a &#8216;vcs st&#8217; should show that file as unknown status. In that way ensuring a clean status before running the tests can help avoid this. However this won&#8217;t work well in an automated fashion because there are often unversioned files, and you typically want to run the tests before committing anyway.<br /><br />2) A time or two I thought I had completely removed/renamed a dependency but forgot to clean up an import somewhere along the line. Even though the original .py file was gone, a .pyc file by the old name still existed, which allowed the lingering import to work. Again however, for anyone else getting a fresh checkout or release, this file would not be avaible and the app would be unusable.<br /><br />How can you avoid having problems like this? Well, from a myopic viewpoint you could have your test suite delete any .pyc files before running. Then to address the first issue, you could also test that a &#8216;vcs st&#8217; has no unknown files, and explicitly ignore any unversioned files you expect. But still, other things could creep up. And while having another machine as your &#8220;buildbot&#8221; would avoid the first issue, you are still prone to an attack from the second. To really make sure you are testing with the same stuff that you release, you need to be testing releases. In other words, you need to be putting your version through your shipping process, whatever that is, and then testing the final product.<br /><br />So now that I&#8217;ve realized this is what I should be doing, I&#8217;m not quite sure what the simplest and easiest way to do it in an automated fashion is. For python, perhaps this could be achieved by getting a fresh export/checkout of the code in a temporary directory, adding that directory to sys.path, and importing and running the tests. I am sure this is a common problem; is there a common solution?</div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Andy</div>
<div class='content'>
I had this problem the other day releasing some code at work. <BR/><BR/>The way I do a release is to run my release script, which reads in file lists scattered around the program, copies them to a new place, compiles them and runs all the tests. It then runs a make clean(*) and builds a tar ball. The file lists are used for generating the makefiles, so all the dependencies are explicitly listed.<BR/><BR/>To release, I untar it into another teams subversion repository, add it and commit. <BR/><BR/>It sounded pretty foolproof to me. So, I untarred it, ran &#8220;svn add&#8221;, then tried compiling it, testing it etc and everything worked. I checked &#8220;svn stat&#8221; to make sure I wasn&#8217;t going to commit anything by accident, and it all looked fine.<BR/><BR/>The next day, I had an email telling me that I broke the build :-). <BR/><BR/>It turned out that when I was creating the file list used for building the release, I accidentally included a backup file (&#8220;somefile.c~&#8221;) in the list. The tarball included the file (since the release script copies all the files listed), so when I untarred it into the svn repository, the file was put in there. But if you do an svn add, it will skip over such files. So when I committed, the backup file was missing, which then made the makefile barf, because all the files from the file list are dependencies.<BR/><BR/>I can&#8217;t quite think of a good way to prevent this from happening again. <BR/><BR/>(*) This is one step where things could go wrong - if the clean target doesn&#8217;t delete everything, then the release will include files that should be generated.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>jmathes</div>
<div class='content'>
by rapid iteration I mean continuous integration</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>jmathes</div>
<div class='content'>
We have the first problem on our website as well; forgetting to check in a .php file.<BR/><BR/>We don&#8217;t have an automated solution, but rapid iteration helps make it a non-issue.  Basically, we haven&#8217;t trained ourselves to ignore unversioned files, because we&#8217;re used to never having any.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Chad</div>
<div class='content'>
We delete .pycs and .pyos as a BuildBot step.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Andy Friesen</div>
<div class='content'>
I have had great success setting up an acceptance test suite that actually constructs an installer, installs the software, and starts the application.<BR/><BR/>We then test the application by prodding it from outside its process. (eg with Windows messages)</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>James Westby</div>
<div class='content'>
Hey Mike,<BR/><BR/>I&#8217;ve one suggestion that may be appropriate: build a package.<BR/><BR/>If you use &#8220;bzr-builddeb&#8221; then this could be as simple as running &#8220;bzr bd&#8221; every so often, installing the resulting deb, and testing the system version.<BR/><BR/>That would check various things, and would catch exactly the case you describe with not running &#8220;bzr add&#8221;<BR/>on the filename.<BR/><BR/>Thanks,<BR/><BR/>James</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>dsas</div>
<div class='content'>
patch queue manager should do all you require I think.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jose M</div>
<div class='content'>
I think that in the books &#8220;Expert python programming&#8221; and &#8220;Foundations of Agile python development&#8221; cover this topic in depth.</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
